<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The holy scripture clearing it self of scandals: or, An answer to a book written by Richard Farnworth, who is commonly called a Quaker, bearing this title, Truth cleared of scandals. In this answer, you have the substance of a dispute at Harliston in Staffordshire, between Richard Faruworth [sic] and the author, in the yeer 1654. Written by Tho. Pollard, a member of the Church of Christ, gathered in, and about, Leichfield. Whereunto is added, Certain considerations and queries concerning those people called the Quakers; with desire of an answer. As also, a postscript, manifesting their folly in pretending a necessity of using the terms thee and thou to a single person. / By Henry Haggar, a servant of Jesus Christ, and of the congregation of his saints.</title>
            <author>Pollard, Thomas, fl. 1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1655</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 132 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90808</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E857_8</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E842_10</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206619</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865738</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865738</idno>
            <idno type="VID">168186</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90808)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 168186)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 128:E842[10] or 130:E857[8])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The holy scripture clearing it self of scandals: or, An answer to a book written by Richard Farnworth, who is commonly called a Quaker, bearing this title, Truth cleared of scandals. In this answer, you have the substance of a dispute at Harliston in Staffordshire, between Richard Faruworth [sic] and the author, in the yeer 1654. Written by Tho. Pollard, a member of the Church of Christ, gathered in, and about, Leichfield. Whereunto is added, Certain considerations and queries concerning those people called the Quakers; with desire of an answer. As also, a postscript, manifesting their folly in pretending a necessity of using the terms thee and thou to a single person. / By Henry Haggar, a servant of Jesus Christ, and of the congregation of his saints.</title>
                  <author>Pollard, Thomas, fl. 1655.</author>
                  <author>Haggar, Henry.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 54, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by J.C. for R. Moone, at the seven Stars in Paul's Church-yard, neer the great North-door.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1655.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy E.842[10]: "June 9th"; on Thomason copy E.857[8]: "Nou: 4".</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>R. F. --  (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666. --  Truth cleared of scandals --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Quakers --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Taryn Hakala</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:168186:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Holy Scriptures Clearing it ſelf of Scandals: OR, AN ANSWER To a BOOK written by <hi>Richard Farnworth,</hi> who is commonly called a QUAKER, bearing this Title, <hi>Truth cleared of Scandals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this ANSWER, You have the ſubſtance of a Diſpute at <hi>Harliſton</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> between <hi>Richard Farnworth</hi> and the Author, in the yeer 1654.</p>
            <p>Written by <hi>Tho. Pollard,</hi> a member of the Church of Chriſt, gathered in, and about, <hi>Leichfield.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Prov. 18.17.</bibl>
               <p>He that is firſt in his own cauſe, ſeemeth juſt; but his neighbour cometh and ſearcheth him.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Whereunto is added, Certain Conſiderations and Queries concerning thoſe people called Quakers; with deſire of an Anſwer.</p>
            <p>As alſo, a POSTSCRIPT, Manifeſting their folly in pretending a neceſſity of uſing the terms <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou</hi> to a ſingle perſon.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Haggar,</hi> a ſervant of Jeſus Chriſt, and of the Congregations of his Saints.</p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London,</hi> by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>R. Moone,</hi> at the ſeven Stars in <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard, neer the great North-door, 1655.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:168186:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:168186:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He LORD hath been pleaſed to bring us into the World in ſuch an Age, that if we throughly weigh our Mercies, they have been, and are, very great. Surely we may ſay in this Nation, That we are p<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rtakers of ſuch Bleſſings and high Favours, that the Generations paſt have not enjoyed <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> If we call to minde the dayes paſt, what Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition
<pb facs="tcp:168186:3"/>inſtead of a pure Worſhip, our eyes beheld; and what Tyranny was then exerciſed, in forcing Men's Conſciences to ſuch a Worſhip, that was ſo exceeding con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Word of GOD. O that we were ſo ſenſible, as we ſhould, who it is that hath wrought ſuch a deliverance for us: ſurely we may ſay, This is the LORD's doing. O that every Soul that partakes of this Mercy, by being delivered from ſuch Tyranny; that, I ſay, this godly reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were in us, as was in the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Pſalm</hi> 71.6. My praiſe ſhall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually of thee. And, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 145.2. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day will I bleſs thee, and I will praiſe thy Name for ever and ever. O, I ſay, if we conſider how many ſnares have been laid to inſnare poor Creatures with; but we may ſay, Hitherto hath the LORD been with us, and hath broken the ſnares, and ſet us at liberty: yet, my dear Friends, the great Enemy of our ſalvation will be work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and if he cannot carry on his deſigne by Inſtruments that are openly profane, or in a ſuperſtitious habit, he can preſent
<pb facs="tcp:168186:3"/>himſelf in a ſhew of glory, and pretend high things: and ſurely that day is now come upon the earth, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. of a ſubtil people, that was endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to beguile the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> as the ſerpent beguiled <hi>Eve,</hi> and from what? minde, the ſimplicity that is in Chriſt; but, ſaith <hi>Paul, verſ.</hi> 13. For ſuch are falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, deceitful workers, transforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt; and no marvel, for Satan himſelf is tranformed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an Angel of light, therefore it is no great thing, if his Miniſters alſo, be transformed as the Miniſters of Righteouſneſs, whoſe end ſhall be according to their work. But as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the Churches of <hi>Galatia,</hi> ſo I ſay to you, <hi>chap.</hi> 1.8. Though we, or an Angel from heaven, preach any other Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel unto you, then that which we have preached unto you, let him be accurſed: and <hi>John</hi> ſaith in his 2 <hi>Epist.</hi> 10. If there come any unto you, and bring not this Doctrine, receive him not into your houſe, neither bid him God-ſpeed. O, I ſay, with the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, If any ſpeak not according to the
<pb facs="tcp:168186:4"/>Scripture, it is, becauſe they have no light in them. And, Reader, whoſoever thou art that peruſeſt this ſmall Treatiſe, labour for an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partial Spirit; &amp; if any thing be to thy ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction herein, let GOD alone be glorified. I have deſired plainneſs of Speech, and to ſpeak the words of Scripture to anſwer him, whom thou wilt finde is an oppoſer of the Truth, as it is in JESUS; and the LORD give thee underſtanding. <hi>Farewel.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine, in the work of the Lord, to my poor power, <hi>Tho. Pollard.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:168186:4"/>
            <head>The Method obſerved in this BOOK: is, as followeth:</head>
            <p n="1">1. YOu have the unſoundneſs of <hi>Richard Farnworth</hi>'s judgement laid down, in ſix Particulars, as he at the meeting ſtood by to make good; and theſe I deſire the Reader to obſerve.</p>
            <p n="2">2. You have an Anſwer to thoſe things he charges me with, in his Book; where the Reader may ſee, that this poor man is full of lyes, that inſtead of being free from ſin, he too much takes delight in it.</p>
            <p n="3">3. You have that Scripture anſwered that they ſo dwell on, againſt that Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Water-baptiſm, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.17.</p>
            <p n="4">4. To make their folly manifeſt, you have that Cavil anſwered, about the term <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou</hi> to ſingle perſon; Which, ſay they, is a ſin to uſe any other; but by the Scripture in all ages, you will, as it is plain, finde it to be no ſuch thing, as is proved.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:168186:5"/>
            <p n="5">5. You have a diſcovery of the Church of Chriſt, how it cometh to Mount <hi>Sion, Heb.</hi> 12.22. And what perfection I own, and how attained.</p>
            <p n="6">6. You have, what he ſaith in his Book he owns, proved to be lyes, and not accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Truth.</p>
            <p n="7">7. You have his folly manifeſted, and the holy Scripture counſelling you to ſhun the way of ſuch men.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Some Queries propounded; with a deſire of an Anſwer.</p>
            <p>And, Reader, for your better ſatisfaction you have the teſtimony of three faithful Witneſſes, that theſe ſix things <hi>Farnworth</hi> did utter; and alſo what is laid down in his Book, that I here ſay he ſpeaketh falſly of me, they are my witneſſes: and upon what ground I then ſpoke, you have it laid down and witneſſed: and for all the reſt of the company there, was out of Goſpel-order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lawrence Spooner, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſula Spooner, Richard Clewly.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:168186:5"/>
            <head>The Holy Scripture clearing it ſelf of SCANDALS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, you have in this Book the unſoundneſs of <hi>Richard Farnworth</hi>'s Judgement in fix Particulars laid down, which being weighed will diſcover that thoſe Principles in his Book, that he ſaith, He holds, are not really according to the Rules of Truth owned by him, but laid down on purpoſe to deceive.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Richard Farnworth</hi> ſaid, <hi>He was a man wholly free from ſin, and not ſubject to any one temptation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, dear Friends, let us firſt make ſearch into the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, to ſee if any of the Lord's people have ſo boaſted of themſelves, to be in ſuch a condition, while they carried about with them an earthly Tabernacle.</p>
            <p>And firſt we will take notice of <hi>Job;</hi> for it's clear, that he had more ground to have boaſted of perfection then any of theſe men, if we minde what the Lord ſaid of him unto Satan, <hi>Hast thou conſidered my ſervant Job, how there is none like him in all the earth, a perfect and an upright man, one that feareth God and eſcheweth evil?</hi> Job 2.3. Yet though the Lord had ſo ſaid of him, let us ſee what <hi>Job</hi> ſaith of himſelf,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:168186:6"/>read <hi>Job</hi> 9.20. <hi>If I juſtifie my ſelf, my own mouth ſhall condemn me: If I ſay, I am perfect, it ſhall alſo prove me perverſe.</hi> And, Job 42.5. <hi>I have heard of thee by the hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the ear: but now my eyes ſee thee. Wherefore I abhorre my ſelf, and repent in dust and aſhes.</hi> From whence it is plain, That <hi>Job</hi> did ſee imperfection in himſelf, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of it: but if <hi>Job</hi> had been wholly perfect, then there was no need of repentance: for to abhorre that which is good, and to repent of that, muſt needs be wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, See what the Lord ſaith of <hi>David, Acts</hi> 13.22. <hi>I have found David a man after my own heart.</hi> And yet we never finde this man boaſting of perfection; but goes humbly to the Lord, and earneſtly begs of him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.12, 13. <hi>Lord, keep thy ſervant from preſumptuous ſins, leſt they get the dominion over me: ſo ſhall I be innocent from the great offence.</hi> And ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.1. How the Lord is his rock, his fortreſs, his God in whom he will truſt. And <hi>ver.</hi> 29. <hi>For by thee have I run through a troop, and by my God I have leaped over a wall.</hi> And <hi>verſ.</hi> 30. <hi>As for God, his way is perfect, the word of the Lord is tried: he is a buckler to all them that trust in him.</hi> This whole Pſalm, <hi>David</hi> ſpeaks out much of the Lords goodneſs to him; but I do not finde one word of boaſting.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, See what the Lord ſaith of <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Ananias,</hi> Acts 9.15. <hi>He is a choſen veſſel to bear my name; and I will ſhew him how great things he muſt ſuffer for my name's ſake.</hi> Yet ſee what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.18. <hi>I know that in me, that is, in my fleſh, there dwels no good thing: for to will is preſent with me; but how to perform that which is good, I finde not.</hi> For <hi>verſ.</hi> 21. <hi>When I would do good, evil is preſent with me.</hi> And ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.15. <hi>This is a faithful ſaying, and worthy of all acceptation, That Christ Jeſus came into the world to ſave ſinners, of whom I am chief.</hi> By all which we may ſee, that <hi>Paul</hi> hath not a word of ſuch boaſting, but rather cryes out againſt the fleſhly part, how it attends him, and oft-times keeps him from doing that which he would.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:168186:6"/>
            <p>Fourthly, we will ſee what is ſaid of <hi>John,</hi> who was an eminent Apoſtle, who is called that Diſciple whom Jeſus loved; and the Scripture ſaith, He lay in Chriſt's boſome, <hi>John</hi> 13.2,. yet we finde that he and <hi>Peter, Acts</hi> 3.12, to 17. ſaid unto the people, <hi>Ye men of Iſrael, why marvel ye at this? or, why look ye ſo earnestly on us, as though by our own power or holineſs we had made this man to walk?</hi> No, he tells them, <hi>It is the God of Abraham, of Iſaac, and of Jacob; the God of our fathers hath glorified his Son Jeſus, whom ye de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered up. His Name,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter, through faith in his Name, hath made this man ſtrong:</hi> not any thing in them, it's plain, doth he ſet up; but ſaith, It was the man's believing in Jeſus, that prevailed with Jeſus, <hi>who gave him this perfect ſoundneſs in the preſence of you all.</hi> And in <hi>Chap.</hi> 4.29. they pray to the Lord for ſtrength, that they may ſpeak his word with boldneſs. By all which it's plain, That they had no depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance on themſelves, by their looking to the Lord, the Rock of their ſtrength, and their Deliverer in their trouble. And further, ſee what <hi>John</hi> ſaith in his 1 <hi>Epist.</hi> 1.8. <hi>If we ſay, We have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves, and the truth is not in us.</hi> Minde, It is ſuch a deceit, that they that ſay ſo, the Truth is not in them. And <hi>James</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chap.</hi> 3.2. <hi>In many things we offend all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now, dear Friends, we ſee what the Scripture ſaith of theſe men, how high in the Lord's favour they were; yet we do not finde, that any of theſe holy men of God, did ſo juſtifie themſelves as this man.</p>
            <p>Now conſider Reader, and the Lord give thee under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. If theſe men, <hi>Job, David, Paul,</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> whoſe whole work it was, as I may ſay, to keep cloſe to the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of God, to ſee how humbly they walked with God, and how ſweetly the Lord appeared to them in this their heavenly progreſs, as the Scripture is full of Witneſſes, and that they did not boaſt of perfection.</p>
            <p>This then we may learn, that for theſe men in our days, who boaſt of perfection, and ſay, they are free from ſin; and yet make it their whole work, to turn away poor ſouls
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:168186:7"/>from the Truth, I mean, the holy Scripture, and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances: that it's pride in them; for they preſume above what is written, as to call the Scripture carnal, and a dead Letter, and ſay, It will never bring a man to the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of God. Now, that theſe are proud and preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous, and ſelf-willed, ſee what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of the Scripture, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15, 16, 17. <hi>Evil men and ſeducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving, and being deceived: but to keep thee from theſe,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>continue thou in the things thou hast learned, and hast been aſſured of; knowing of whom thou haſt learned them, and that from a child thou haſt known the holy Scriptures, which are able to make thee wiſe unto ſalvation through faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> And he further ſaith, <hi>All Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, and is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſneſs, that the man of God may be perfect, throughly fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed unto all good works.</hi> By all which it's plain, That theſe men are of another mind then the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> for he vindicates the Scripture and Ordinances in all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles: then, I ſay, it is wickedneſs in theſe men to ſpeak againſt the Scripture and Ordinances, as they do; calling it a dead Letter, and carnal; and ſay, That all that is gotten from the Scripture, is but brain-knowledge.</p>
            <p>Now, dear Friends, may we not ſee plainly how they ſtrike at Jeſus Chriſt in his Ordinances, which do ſo lively repreſent him, and which he hath born witneſs to himſelf, and confirmed it to us, to be a ſure Word of Propheſie, by many Signs, and Wonders, and Gifts of the Holy Ghoſt?</p>
            <p>And further, dear Friends, let us not forget how won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully the Lord hath preſerved this Word from the rage of Enemies, not onely in the Generations paſt, but our days have ſpoken out much to us. If we look back to thoſe days of profanation, &amp; wicked toleration, when nothing but ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtition had countenance, and many for conſcience-ſake were ſore oppreſſed: now for us to conſider what we then did ſee, inſtead of pure Ordinances, and to take notice of what we now, through mercy, injoy; we may ſay, the Lord hath
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:168186:7"/>wrought for us wonderfully: which being laid to heart, it may encourage us to follow the holy Commandments of Chriſt Jeſus, though we be reproached and called Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees by theſe men, for obſerving the Primitive Patern: for do but try them by their Works, and you will finde, that they carry on a deſign for Satan, as it appears by the words of one <hi>Foſter</hi> to me at <hi>Coulton</hi> in <hi>Staffordſhire,</hi> who ſaid, <hi>It was all one to them if all Bibles were burnt;</hi> as many of the Lord's people can witneſs. But O you Saints of God! minde the progreſs of the Lords people, how they followed after righteouſneſs, godlineſs, faith, love, patience, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.11, 12.</p>
            <p>Again, let us conſider how patient <hi>Job</hi> was under the hand of the Lord, ſaying, <hi>The Lord giveth, and the Lord taketh away, bleſſed be the name of the Lord.</hi> And he is brought in by the Apoſtle, <hi>James</hi> 5.10. <hi>Take, my brethren, the Prophets for an example of ſuffering affliction, and of patience: and how they are accounted happy that endure. Ye have heard of the patience of Job, and have ſeen the end of the Lord, that the Lord is very pitiful, and of tender mercy to all them that wait patiently on him.</hi> And ſo we finde <hi>David</hi> an excellent patern for obedience: he made haſt and delayed not to keep God's Commandments, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.60. <hi>O</hi>(ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>) <hi>how I love thy law! it is my meditation all the day. Thou through thy commandments haſt made me wiſer then my ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; yea, I have more underſtanding then my teachers, for thy teſtimonies are my meditation. I underſtand more then the ancient, becauſe I have kept thy precepts. I have refrained my feet from every evil way, that I may keep thy word.</hi> Thus, dear Friends, mind <hi>David</hi> and theſe men, and you will finde they as far differ as light and darkneſs; and if <hi>David</hi> had ſo much wiſdom in this way of keeping God's Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and Ordinances of Chriſt Jeſus, are proud men and fools, becauſe they conſent not to the wholſome words of Chriſt, and to the Doctrine which is according to godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: he is proud, or a fool, as ſaith the margin, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3, 4.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:168186:8"/>
            <p>O what will theſe ſcorners do, when the Lord comes from Heaven with his Saints to render vengeance on all that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel? minde that, and you may eaſily ſee, that all them that deride the Word and Ordinances of Chriſt, under what term and title ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever called, whether Quakers, Ranters or other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachers of God, his Son, his Saints, his Ordinances, and trample the Blood of Chriſt under their feet, and do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpight to the Spirit of Grace, and ſadden the hearts of his dear Ones, and cauſe the Truth of God to be evill ſpoken of: O to ſuch I ſay, it had been better for them that they had never known the way of Truth, then after they have known it, to turn from the holy Commandment delivered unto them: but it is happened unto them according to the true Proverb, <hi>The dog is turned to his own vomit again, and the ſow that was waſhed to her wallowing in the mire,</hi> as ſaith the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21, 22.</p>
            <p>But O ye Saints, and ſpiritual Chriſtians, who are troubled to hear the Truth of Chriſt abuſed by ſuch men; See what <hi>Paul</hi>'s counſel is, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>To you who are troubled, reſt with us; abide in the doctrine of Chriſt, quit you like men, be ſtrong in the Lord, labour to be ſtedfaſt, unmove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, alwayes abounding in the work of the Lord; for you know your labour is not in vain in the Lord.</hi> Rom. 1.15, 58. <hi>The Lord hath promiſed to you ſuch a reward, that all theſe evil-ſpeakers cannot rob you of. And ſeeing it is a righteous thing with God, to recompence tribulation on them that trouble you, be incouraged to run the race that is ſet before you.</hi> Follow the holy Commandments, and the pattern of the Apoſtles, as they followed Chriſt, you may be born up above all the diſcouragements you meet with, by ſuch as ſpeak evil of the holy Scripture and Ordinances, which you own as a Rule to walk by; for whatever is done againſt any of the Lord's people, that are found doing his Commandments, Jeſus Chriſt will take all that is done againſt them, as done to himſelf, as you may ſee in that <hi>Acts</hi> 9. by the words Chriſt ſaid to <hi>Saul:</hi> for you are dear in his ſight, and are
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:168186:8"/>continually before him, and his delight is with you, his heart is towards you; there ſhall be no want to them that fear him: <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.14. <hi>Bleſſed are they that do his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that they may have right to the tree of life, and may enter into the gates through the city.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But O <hi>Farnworth,</hi> and thoſe with thee, that ſo impudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly boaſt of perfection, and judge all to be in darkneſs, that throw not away the rule of Truth, as you do; O call to mind your ſelf-conceitedneſs. Had you ever ſuch ground of boaſting as <hi>Job, David, Paul,</hi> and <hi>John?</hi> The Lord never ſaid ſo of you, or any that ever went your way, as he ſaith of theſe men, that you were after his heart, as <hi>David;</hi> or his choſen, as <hi>Paul;</hi> or his beloved Diſciple, as <hi>John;</hi> or ſuch a one, for doing that which was good, and hating that which was evil, as <hi>Job,</hi> that the Lord ſaith, There was none like him in all the Land of <hi>Uz<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Yet we do not finde any of theſe men thus juſtifie themſelves, as you do; and they never judged ſo raſhly of others, as you do of all men that are not of your minde, calling them carnal, and ſaying that they are devils, as I can ſhew under ſome of your hands: ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly you are coming on apace to them that ſay they are God; but your glorying is not good; for you glory in appearance, having a kinde of voluntary humility; but this will not ſtand you in ſtead, becauſe you go about to ſet up your ſelves and not the Lord; your own way, and not his way: and therefore you are the greater Hypocrites. And ſee what <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith of all ſuch, <hi>Iob</hi> 8.13. <hi>The hypocrites hope ſhall periſh.</hi> And Job 20.5. <hi>The joy of the hypocrite is but for a moment.</hi> And <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>Prov.</hi> 11.9. <hi>An hypocrite with his mouth deſtroyeth his neighbour.</hi> And do not you with your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luding tongues, and out-ſide holineſs, throwing dirt in the face of Truth; and as much as in you lies, deſtroying all men by your Doctrine, which had its riſe from Hell and darkneſs, and now raigns in the children of diſobedience, ſuch as you, who minde nothing leſs, then the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Ordinances, as they were delivered to the Saints, and committed to faithful men, and are of great uſe to all the Lord's people; which word diſcovers all your
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:168186:9"/>wayes to be from Hell and darkneſs, as in the following diſcourſe it will be manifeſt, that your Opinions are hatch'd in Hell, and never came from above, Whence, <hi>Iames</hi> ſaith, every good and perfect gift comes: and then it will plainly appear, that all that follow you are in the error, and are under a great deluſion, to take your bare word for what you affirm, yea, though it croſs the Scripture never ſo much<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But O conſider, ye poor deluded ones, firſt, <hi>The heart of man is deceitful above all things,</hi> Jer. 17.9. Secondly, <hi>He that truſteth his own heart, is a fool,</hi> Prov. 28.26.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that this <hi>Farnworth</hi> affirmed, <hi>That when</hi> Paul <hi>ſpoke thoſe words in the ſeventh of the</hi> Romans, <hi>where he cries out of a body of death, and of the warfare he had in himſelf, he ſaid, That Paul was not converted.</hi> To which I anſwered, <hi>O man, minde thy error! what</hi> Paul, <hi>a Meſſenger of the Goſpel, and ſo eminent an Apoſtle of Chriſt, and unconverted?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here let us try by the Scripture whether it be ſo or no: firſt, ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 9.5, 6. When the Voice from Heaven, which Voice was Chriſt, that ſaid to him, <hi>Saul, Saul, why perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuteſt thou me? He trembling and aſtoniſhed, ſaid, Lord, what wouldſt thou have me to do?</hi> The Lord ſent him to <hi>Ananias:</hi> and when he had manifeſted his Faith in Chriſt, by his obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to Chriſt, he ſtraightway preached Chriſt, in the Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues, to be the Son of God. And further, ſee <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. of this ninth <hi>Chapter,</hi> where it was made plain to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. <hi>And he was with them, coming in, and going out at Ieruſalem: and he ſpake boldly in the Name of Ieſus Chriſt, and diſputed againſt the Grecians.</hi> And this whole Chapter makes it evident both in what he did and ſuffered, that he was converted. And further, ſee <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Paul a ſervant of Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> then ſure converted, elſe no fit Servant for ſo great a work; and not onely ſo, but, <hi>called to be an Apoſtle, ſeparated unto the Goſpel of God.</hi> And pray you minde who called him to this great work, not himſelf, but the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2. <hi>The Holy Ghoſt ſaid, Separate me Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas and Saul, for the work whereunto I have called them.</hi> By
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:168186:9"/>which it is plain, he was converted before, as I at that time told thee.</p>
            <p>Then thou wouldſt turn it, and didſt ſay that he ſpake of his condition before converſion in that <hi>Rom.</hi> 7. And this is as falſe as the other, if the words be weighed, verſ. 22. to 25. <hi>For I delight in the law of God after the inward man.</hi> Pray you minde; at that time he did ſee a law in his members warring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of his minde.</p>
            <p>Nay further, if all this had been before converſion, then how could he have ſaid as he ſaith verſ. 25. that with his minde he ſerved the Law of God? for it is evident that his minde before converſion was onely to perſecute the Church and people of God. And here we will bring his own words to witneſs, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.9. <hi>I</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>am the leaſt of the Apoſtles not worthy to be called an Apoſtle:</hi> minde the reaſon, <hi>Becauſe I perſecuted the Church of God.</hi> By all which we may plainly ſee how contrary to the Scripture, and unfound, this opinion is. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore take heed, poor ſouls, of following men any further then they follow Chriſt, and keep his way. And you deluded ones, that ſpeak againſt the holy Scripture in the whole, it is no wonder that you make ſuch tearing it in pieces as you do. And though you uſe the Scripture ſo frequent in your writing, it is out of ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilty to enſnare ſouls, as that great deceiver did to Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 4.6.</p>
            <p>But one word to the Lords people. Take Scripture-argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to fight againſt Deceivers: and for your progreſs in the Lords way, take <hi>Jeremiah</hi>'s counſel, Chap. 6.16. <hi>Stand ye in the way, and ſee, and ask for the old paths: where is the good way? and walk therein.</hi> And then minde the promiſe: <hi>Ye ſhall finde reſt for your ſouls.</hi> And how we may find the way of the Lord, read <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.20. <hi>To the law, and to the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony: if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is no light in them.</hi> Compared with <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.8, 9.</p>
            <p>The Third thing, <hi>Farnworth</hi> affirmed, <hi>that where</hi> John <hi>ſpake thoſe words,</hi> If we ſay we have no ſin, we deceive our ſelves; <hi>he ſaid,</hi> John <hi>did not here ſpeak of himſelf; but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:168186:10"/>the people to whom he ſpake theſe words were unconver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer to this, minde the Apoſtles words, 1 <hi>Iob.</hi> 1.3. <hi>That which we have ſeen and heard, that we declare unto you, that ye may have fellowſhip with us; and truely our fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip is with the Father and the Son.</hi> And, <hi>Theſe things we write unto you, that your joy may be full:</hi> and this was joy to them: Chap. 3.2. <hi>Now are we the ſons of God, and it doth not yet appear what we ſhall be: but we know that when he ſhall appear we ſhall be like him; for we ſhall ſee him as he is.</hi> And in Chap. 2.24, 25. <hi>Let that therefore abide in you, which ye have heard from the beginning: if that ſhall abide in you, ye alſo ſhall continue in the Son and in the Father: and this is the promiſe he hath promiſed us, even eternal life.</hi> And <hi>John</hi> ſaith, verſ. 21 of this chap. 2. <hi>I have not written unto you becauſe ye know not the truth, but becauſe ye know it.</hi> By all which it is plain they were built on the foundation, for elſe it had been abſurd for the Apoſtle to have exhorted them to abide in Chriſt and his commandments, if not converted; for then the exhortation was of no uſe; and beſide, it is very im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper to adviſe any man to keep that which he never had.</p>
            <p>Again, 2. The Apoſtle doth here preſs them to perſevere, and to go on, and to walk in the light; then they muſt know it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I do not finde any Epiſtle written to any but to the Saints; as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.7.1 <hi>Cor</hi> 2.2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. By all which it is plain, To the Saints at <hi>Rome,</hi> To the Church at <hi>Corinth,</hi> To the Saints at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> To the Church at <hi>Galatia,</hi> Saints at <hi>Philippi,</hi> Saints at <hi>Coloſſe</hi> Saints at <hi>Theſſalonica.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Apoſtle put himſelf in: <hi>If WE ſay WE have no ſin, WE deceive our ſelves.</hi> Here he puts himſelf one of the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p>Not that I go about, as <hi>Farnworth</hi> falſly ſaith, to plead a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in ſin: for I do own, that believers, as they are in Chriſt, are juſtified from ſin, and God is ſatisfied with his Son, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith; he looked on the travel of his ſoul and was ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. But that which I ſay, is this, That believers do ſee ſome de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:168186:10"/>in themſelves, in their outward man, as they carry about with them an earthly tabernacle: but through grace, they over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come all defects by degrees.</p>
            <p>And we will ſee what the Scripture faith from the mouth of other godly witneſſes. See <hi>Solomon,</hi> 1 King. 8.46. <hi>There is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>no man that ſinneth not:</hi> with <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.9. <hi>Who can ſay, I have made my heart clean, I am pure from my ſin?</hi> With <hi>Eccl.</hi> 7.20. Saith the wiſe Preacher, <hi>There is not a juſt man upon earth, that doth good, and ſinneth not.</hi> Now then, I ſay with the Apoſtle, <hi>Let God</hi> and his Word <hi>be true, and all men lyers.</hi> And I do appeal to every godly ſoul, for to witneſs this, who are ſenſible of fleſh and ſelf appearing in them at one time or other. But dear Saints, look up to the Lord for ſtrength, and let us be ſure, if we would conquer, to fight with ſpiritual weapons: and let us take heed of ſuch an opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that will be judge himſelf in his own cauſe, and will not be tried by the Scripture, accounting it dead and carnal, and of no uſe to bring men to Chriſt. As when I asked <hi>Farnworth</hi> how he would witneſs the truth of what he affirmed, in that he deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Scripture; he laid his hand on his heart, and ſaid, <hi>I witneſs this.</hi> Now minde this deluſion, as I ſaid before what <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith, Chap. 17.9. 1. <hi>The heart of man is deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful above all things, and deſperately wicked; who can know it? 2. He that truſteth in his own heart, is a fool,</hi> Prov. 28.26.</p>
            <p>And now dear friends, let us take counſel of the Lord, to <hi>try the ſpirits whether they be of God: for many falſe prophets are gone out into the world,</hi> 1 Joh. 4.1. And verſ. 6. <hi>We are of God: he that knoweth God, heareth us; and he that is not of God, heareth not us. Hereby know we the ſpirit of truth and the ſpirit of error.</hi> From whence we may honeſtly argue, that if they, and they onely, be the friends of God, that walk in obedience to the commands of God; then they muſt needs be enemies that oppoſe. But the firſt is clear, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.14. <hi>Ye are my friends, if ye do whatſoever I command you</hi> with <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.23. <hi>If any man love me he will keep my words; and my Father will love him.</hi> And 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.2<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. <hi>For this is the love of God, that we keep his commandments; and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:168186:11"/>are not grievous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, dear friends, let us embrace that advice that <hi>Peter</hi> gives, 2 Epiſt. 3.17, 18. <hi>Beware leſt you being led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with the errour of the wicked, fall from your own ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fastneſs.</hi> And to prevent you from falling, his counſel is. <hi>But grow in grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now is the hour of temptation: for if theſe be not wicked errours, I know not what is: I mean theſe which are laid down to your view, which <hi>Farnworth</hi> did ſtand by to vindicate, if his own teſtimony may ſtand. O then, what need have all the Lords people to be upon their watch, now Satan by his inſtruments is ſifting poor ſouls out of the Truth, if he can! It is high time to look to our foundation, that we be built on the Rock Chriſt, that you be firmly knit to him, and made one with him; and then the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt you.</p>
            <p>And you ſtrong Chriſtians, help the weak Lambs of Jeſus Chriſt, that they may grow in that good way of Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, that the Saints of old have walked in. O be ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up one another by way of remembrance of the good path of Chriſt, which diſcovers fully all the by-paths of iniquity. Oh, I ſay, let there not be a want of care among you in your ſeveral Societies, to watch over one another, leſt any be entangled by theſe ſeducing ſpirits, and overcome, I ſay, by theſe that throw aſide all the Laws and Ordinances of the Lord Jeſus, as they were delivered to the Saints, and ought now by us to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: for you know what the Scripture ſaith of them that turn from the way of Truth; <hi>It had been better for them that they had never known it, then after they have known it, to turn from the holy commandment delivered unto them.</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21.</p>
            <p>O then, I ſay to all you that are employed in the Lords work, whether by Office or Gift, that are faithful Stewards, diligent in feeding the flock of Chriſt; remember what the Lord ſaith to ſuch: <hi>When the chief Shepherd ſhall appear. ye ſhall receive a crown of glory that fadeth not away,</hi> 1 Pet. 5.4. And ſaith <hi>Daniel<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Chap. 12.3. <hi>They that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the firmament, and they that turn many to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:168186:11"/>righteouſneſs, as the ſtars for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if theſe men be ſo forward in pulling down the Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Chriſt, you have greater encouragement to follow Chriſt in his way.</p>
            <p n="1">1. You have his own preſence promiſed (<hi>Matth.</hi> 2820.) in the work.</p>
            <p n="2">2. See your reward after the work, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.27, 28.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Farnworth</hi> affirmed <hi>that Chriſt had not a viſible Church in the world;</hi> and ſcornfully ſaid to me. <hi>What, a Church in the world!</hi> I anſwered, <hi>Yea, in the world though not of the world, but gathered out of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And 1. See what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.2. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Church of God which is at Corinth, ſanctified in Chriſt Jeſus, called to be Saints, with all that in every place call on the Name of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Reader, pray you minde, this muſt needs be a viſible Church:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe this Epiſtle is directed to a viſible place, <hi>Corinth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is as clear, that here were men, and that under this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral term <hi>brethren;</hi> verſ. 10. <hi>I beſeech you brethren by our Lord Jeſus, that you all ſpeak the ſame thing, and that there be no diviſion among you, but that you be perfectly joyned to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in the ſame minde, and in the ſame judgment.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Paul</hi> makes mention of houſholds, verſ. 11. the houſe of <hi>Cloe;</hi> and <hi>Stephanas,</hi> verſ. 16.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He ſpeaks of perſons by name, as <hi>Criſpus</hi> and <hi>Gaius,</hi> and others. By all which it is clear, this poor man is much beſide the Rule of Truth.</p>
            <p>Again, ſee what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith unto the Churches of <hi>Galatia;</hi> Chap. 1.1. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Churches of Galatia.</hi> And mind <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.1. <hi>Commend unto you Phebe our ſiſter, which is a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Church at Cenchrea.</hi> Minde how full the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is to prove this thing, and makes manifeſt the blindneſs of this mans underſtanding, that will thus oppoſe the Truth that is ſo full of wintneſſes.</p>
            <p>And how doth the holy Ghoſt write to the ſeven Churches in <hi>Aſia?</hi> And how, I pray you <hi>Farnworth,</hi> will you anſwer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:168186:12"/>that place in <hi>Acts</hi> 8. when <hi>Steven</hi> was ſtoned, and the Church at <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> all ſcattered? 1. This muſt needs be a viſible company, becauſe they were viſibly ſcattered. 2. They were at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which was a viſible place, the Scripture is full for. 3. See whither they were ſcattered; ſome into <hi>Judea,</hi> and ſome into <hi>Samaria.</hi> And <hi>Saul</hi> he made havock of the Church, verſ. 3:</p>
            <p>But here we may ſee your ſubtilty and cunning craftineſs whereby you lie in wait to deceive: for if you can bring poor ſouls to this, That God hath not a viſible Church in the world, then you may eaſily perſwade them to throw aſide all the viſible Rule of Scripture, and ſo make all Doctrine and Church-Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of none effect: and thus you would put out the eyes of poor ſouls, and then bring them to ſee with your eyes; and then your words they may quickly learn, which are onely thus, to ſay they muſt hearken to a light within: but, <hi>if the light in thee be darkneſs, how great is that darkneſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here thy darkneſs doth appear, in denying a viſible Church, which is ſo plainly proved.</p>
            <p>But Reader, by theſe men, the Rule of tryal to try the Spirits withal, is thrown away, and become of no uſe to theſe men, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be for advantage.</p>
            <p>But dear ſouls, conſider, firſt, that the heart is deceitful; and he that truſteth to it, is a fool. And then to have no other judge in thy own caſe but thy ſelf, (as this is their principle) how doth it open a door to looſneſs? And many poor ſouls have been ſo far miſled as to ſay, That which men call ſin doth as highly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour God, as that which men call prayer or holy performances: I ſay, theſe things I have heard uttered by mouth, and have ſeen in print: and if this be not ſad and dangerous, I know no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>But to you of the Church of Chriſt that are by theſe men cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Phariſees and outward Jews, and branded with reproach; ſee what <hi>Peter</hi> ſaith, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.20, <hi>If when ye do well and ſuffer for it ye take it patiently, this is acceptable with God: for even hereunto were ye called, becauſe Chriſt alſo ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for us, leaving us an example that we ſhould follow his ſteps.</hi> And in Chap. 4. verſ. 14. he ſaith, <hi>If ye be reproached
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:168186:12"/>for the Name of Chriſt, happie are ye: for the Spirit of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and of God reſteth upon you. On their part he is evil ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of, but on your part he is glorified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And further, friends, let us call to minde how ſweetly the Lord hath appeared to us in the uſe of Ordinances; and then I hope you will take heed of entertaining ſuch an opinion, that is ſo wicked as to overthrow all the Ordinances of Chriſt that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to his Church. O but labour for oneneſs of ſpirit, and you will be terrible to all your enemies as an army with banners.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, <hi>Farnworth</hi> affirmed, that <hi>all Ordinances ceaſed when Chriſt aſcended and gave the Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, dear friends, let us not take the thing for granted, upon his bare word, becauſe he ſaith ſo; but let us be like the <hi>Bere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> ſearch the Scripture, to ſee if the thing be ſo.</p>
            <p>And firſt, we will minde the commiſſion, and the time when Chriſt gave it; and that is clear it was after his reſurrection, as the laſt chapter of <hi>Matthew</hi> witneſſeth at large. If ſo, then it muſt be that this commiſſion was given when Chriſt entered into his Kingly office; and this his own words make good: for now ſaith Chriſt, <hi>All power is given into my hands in heaven and in earth: go ye therefore and teach all nations, and baptize them.</hi> And the continuance of theſe Ordinances is plain, in the laſt verſe: <hi>Lo</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>I am with you alway, to the end of the world.</hi> Now this is to me ſo ſtrong an argument, that ſurely it will make a gracious heart tremble to deny it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If this be true that <hi>Farnworth</hi> affirms, then ſee how ſhort a time Ordinances were to be of uſe in the world. Read <hi>Acts</hi> 1.1. <hi>The former treatiſe have I made, O Theophilus, of all that Jeſus began to do and teach, until the day he was taken up, after that he through the holy Ghoſt had given com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment unto the Apoſtles whom he had choſen, to whom alſo he ſhewed himſelf alive after his paſſion by many infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proofs, being ſeen of them fourty days.</hi> Pray ye minde: it ſeems then by this mans judgement, that Ordinances were to be of uſe but fourty days: which is very corrupt. And further, then the end of the world ſhould have been, if this he ſaith be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:168186:13"/>true, when Chriſt aſcended: two great abſurdities; 1. To <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that Ordinances were of uſe but fourty days. 2. Then it muſt follow alſo, that at Chriſts aſcenſion ſhould be the end of the world: and ſo all the promiſes of the Spirit had been nothing worth.</p>
            <p>But minde, dear friends, what Chriſt ſaith to his Apoſtles: <hi>Tarry at Ieruſalem, and go not out thence, till ye have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived power from on high: and when the holy Ghoſt is come upon you, ye ſhall be witneſſes unto me both in Ieruſalem, and in all Iudea, and in Samaria, and in all the uttermoſt parts of the earth;</hi> Acts 1. at large. By all which it is plain, if the Scripture may be heard to ſpeak for it ſelf, that the Apoſtles were not ſo fully fitted for that great work, to preach the Goſpel to every creature, until Chriſt aſcended &amp; gave the Spirit. Read <hi>Acts</hi> 2.3, 4, 5. And Chriſt told them (<hi>Ioh.</hi> 14, 26.) the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he would ſend the Comforter, which is the holy Ghoſt: and this is his work; <hi>He ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your remembrance, whatſoever I have ſaid unto you.</hi> Then minde; If it be the work of this Spirit of Truth that cometh from the Father and the Son, to bring to their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance what Chriſt before ſpake to them; then it is plain, that the commiſſion is one part of what Chriſt ſpake to them before his aſcenſion. Yea, there is much wrapt up in it, that the Spirit was to inmind the Apoſtles of; and not them onely, but all thoſe now, that carry on the ſame work, by the ſame rule, for one and the ſame end; namely, To glorifie God, to be uſeful to his Church, and to all men.</p>
            <p>Now we will ſee how the minde of Chriſt was when he was gone to heaven; and we ſhall finde he was of the ſame minde to maintain Ordinances, as well as when he was on the earth: and for this, ſee a plain text of Scripture, <hi>Acts 9.6. And the Lord ſaid unto Saul, Ariſe, and go into the city, and it ſhall be told thee what thou muſt do.</hi> And as the Lord ſent him in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the citie, minde the end the Lord had, in ſending <hi>Ananias,</hi> who told him as he had received from Chriſt, what <hi>Saul</hi> muſt do: and this was one thing that <hi>Ananias</hi> told him, as it is plain, <hi>Acts</hi> 22.14, 15, 16. firſt, that he was choſen of the Lord, that he ſhould know his will, and ſee that Juſt One, and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:168186:13"/>ſhould hear the voice of his mouth: <hi>for</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou ſhalt be his witneſs to all men, of what thou haſt ſeen and heard. And now why tarrieſt thou? ariſe, and be baptized, and waſh away thy ſins, calling on the name of the Lord.</hi> By which it is plain, that Chriſt was of the ſame minde to maintain Ordinances in his Church, after his aſcenſion, as before.</p>
            <p>But when I inſtanced theſe Scriptures, <hi>Farnworth</hi> ſaid, that this was not Water-baptiſm that <hi>Paul</hi> was baptized with, but the Baptiſm of the Spirit; as many can witneſs.</p>
            <p>But I think no ſober man will be of this mans judgement: for,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider, if it were the baptiſm of the Spirit, it were too high for <hi>Ananias,</hi> as he was a diſciple, to carry on: and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out queſtion, we ſhould have found <hi>Ananias</hi> anſwering <hi>Paul,</hi> as <hi>Iohn</hi> confeſſeth in another place; <hi>I indeed baptize with water; but there is one coming after me, he ſhall baptize with the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It would be very abſurd to give that to men, that is Chriſts proper and peculiar right. But it is no wonder to finde theſe men thus dealing with Chriſt himſelf, that will thus wickedly ſpeak againſt his Ordinances.</p>
            <p>But then he asked me whether my baptiſm waſhed away ſin. I told him I could prove that Water-baptiſm was an Ordinance of Chriſt, being adminiſtred on right ſubjects, which are men and women when they believe; and yeelding obedience to it as a command of Chriſt, I had <hi>the anſwer of a good conſcience;</hi> and this no man can have, but by the waſhing away of ſin: for obedience and godlineſs hath the promiſe of this life, and of that which is to come: for, <hi>bleſſed are they that do his command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> But I do not affirm that any man can have ſalvation by vertue of his obedience; but this I ſay, that the obedient, and they onely, are within the promiſes; and it will be aſſuredly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to them: for, <hi>faithful is he that promiſeth, and he will perform it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O then, dear Saints, to you that prize the holy command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Chriſt, and yet live in the uſe of them, though theſe men ſo ſpeak againſt them; I ſhall give you another Scripture, to ſhew Chriſts care of his Church, that it may be well ordered
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:168186:14"/>according to his minde, and how long Ordinances are to ſtand: beſide that of the commiſſion, that ſhews to the end of the world; this in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4, 8. which plainly holdeth out the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of it: <hi>When he aſcended up on high, he gave ſome A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, ſome Paſtors and Teachers.</hi> And let us minde the end Chriſt had in ſo doing; which is, <hi>for the perfecting of the Saints:</hi> by which it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that Chriſt did well know that the Church would ſtand in need of help from him. Ah Saints! ſee his care of you: prize it then. Secondly, that the <hi>work of the Miniſtery</hi> might be carried on in the Church and world, for the inlarging of his kingdom. Thirdly, that <hi>the body might be edified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Chriſt having thus carefully provided for his Church, and for all men, that the Goſpel might be preached to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; then he tells us how long Ordinances ſhall ſtand, verſ.13. <hi>Till we all come in the unity of the faith.</hi> Then it is plain, that Ordinances are yet of force: for thoſe <hi>who are beloved for the Fathers ſake,</hi> the Lord hath ſaid he muſt bring in. The Lord haſten the day of their coming in, that the Gentiles fulneſs may be compleated. Secondly, the Church ſhall be brought <hi>to a perfect man, unto the ſtature of the fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi> But yet we ſee much incompleatneſs: but O that we were more look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for this day.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, we may ſee another end Chriſt had, verſ.14. <hi>That we henceforth be no more children toſſed to and fro with every winde of doctrine: by the ſlight of men, and cunning craftineſs whereby they lie in wait to deceive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we well weigh theſe words, we may ſee that Chriſt did well know, ſo many hundred yeers ago, what would come to paſs in the laſt times. And ſure now is the time: for we ſee men riſen up, pretending high attainments, not in a ſuperſtitious habit, but in a ſhew of glory, and filled with feigned words and fair ſpeeches, deceive the hearts of the ſimple; and thus they lie in wait to deceive: when they cannot work downright at once with a man, then they will work by degrees: as firſt, to benum or deaden his affection to Ordinances, and put him out of love with ſomething that the Church lives in the practiſe of; as breaking of bread, calling it carnal: and when they have drawn
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:168186:14"/>away his affection, then they endeavour to ſtifle him in his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo enſnare him. I ſpeak what I know in this thing.</p>
            <p>But you dear Saints, that are faithful to the principles of Truth, labour to embrace that Exhortation, and to walk worthy of that commendation that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.1, 2. In the firſt verſe you have the Exhortation, in theſe words: <hi>Be ye followers of me, even as I alſo am of Christ.</hi> The commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is in theſe words: <hi>Now I praiſe you brethren, that ye remember me in all things, and keep the Ordinances as I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered them unto you.</hi> And if this be well pleaſing in the ſight of God, that we keep his Ordinances as they were deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his ſervants, and they had this authority from above, and his preſence with them in the work; then it is plain, that theſe men who thus ſet themſelves to overthrow the Ordinances of Chriſt, as they were once delivered, are the deceivers. For they that will deny a viſible Church, that the Scripture is ſo full to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and will ſay, that all Ordinances ceaſed when Chriſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended: then <hi>Paul</hi> was too blame to commend the Church at <hi>Corinth</hi> for keeping that which Chriſt had put an end to at his aſcention, if what <hi>Farnworth</hi> ſayes be true. Again, it is plain, that <hi>Paul</hi> was a Perſecutor at Chriſt's aſcention: then minde, it muſt be that Chriſt did ſhew to <hi>Paul</hi> this, That he was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of commendation that did keep the Ordinances; and if what <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake were by the Spirit of God, as without all queſtion he did, then it muſt follow, that theſe have a ſpirit of deluſion coming from hell and darkneſs, that ſpits out ſuch venome againſt the Ordinances of Chriſt Jeſus, that is ſo fully confirmed to us by ſo ſtrong an Obligation of his own making. <hi>I will be with you:</hi> minde, if the Lord Jeſus will be with them that obey him, then ſurely ſatan will be &amp; is with them that go contrary to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of Chriſt. And minde <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.16. <hi>To whom ye yeild your ſelves ſervants to obey, his ſervants ye are; whether of ſin unto death, or obedience unto righteouſneſs.</hi> And I am ſure it is well for every ſoul that is found faithful to the death, for they ſhall receive a crown of life that fadeth not away, which God the righteous Judge will give to all thoſe that long and look for his appearing. O then they are the only happy men and women that are faithful in obedience to every command of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:168186:15"/>
            <p>The ſixth thing, <hi>Farnworth</hi> affirmed, <hi>That the Scripture was not of any uſe to any man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> till he was brought into the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of them that writ the Scriptures.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then it muſt follow, that the Scripture is onely in uſe for men in Chriſt, and not to bring them to Chriſt; for, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Holy men of God, ſpake as they were moved by the holy Ghoſt.</hi> Then minde, 1. The abſurdity will be this, that the Scripture is not of uſe to make men holy; but uſeful onely to holy men, becauſe holy. 2. Then this muſt follow, that the Scripture is not of uſe to teach or ſhew men the way to Chriſt; but to them that are taught or brought to him without it. 3. To deſtroy preaching upon this ground, namely, to convince and convert ſouls to Chriſt, muſt needs deſtroy Faith alſo: for ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>Faith cometh by hearing;</hi> and if by it, then not without it, minde that: ſo then to take away the cauſe, the effect will ceaſe. And it is plain by the Scripture, that the Goſpels preaching, is the cauſe of mens believing; for ſaith <hi>Paul, verſ.</hi> 14. <hi>How ſhall they believe in him, of whom they have not heard?</hi> O then Reader, minde, how far this Opinion will plunge a poor ſoul, whoſe condition is ſuch, that he cannot pleaſe God without Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. <hi>Without faith it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> minde, <hi>to pleaſe God.</hi> And in <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.23. <hi>Whatſoever is not of faith is ſin:</hi> ſo then, to deny the Ordinance of preaching, by which Faith comes, muſt needs tend to deſtroy Faith, and then pleaſe God who can. But let us weigh the deſign of theſe men a little: if they can once bring a poor ſoul into this condition to diſown the Scripture when he moſt ſtands in need of it; that is to ſay, to bring him to Chriſt, and to ſhew him how he ought walk ſo as to pleaſe God: I ſay, if once the poor creature be brought into ſuch a condition, then he knows he can eaſily keep him from priſing it at all.</p>
            <p>But let us ſee how this croſſes the end of God's ſending his Son into the World: <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>chap.</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world that he gave his onely begotten Son into the world that whoſoever believeth on him ſhould not periſh, but have ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life.</hi> Again, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. witneſſes, that Chriſt was ſent of the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:168186:15"/>Father, to be a light to them that ſit in darkneſs, and are in the ſhadow of death, and to guide our feet into the way of peace. And how ſhould we know this great love of the Father, much leſs believe it, without the Goſpels preaching? Again, Chriſt ſaith, <hi>He came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance;</hi> and, <hi>he came to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt.</hi> By all which it is plain, that the end of the Goſpels preaching to every creature, was not becauſe every creature did believe this, but that they might hear and believe. Again, if thoſe three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, <hi>Act.</hi> 2. were converted by the Goſpel, then not without it; and them of <hi>Samaria</hi> by the Goſpel, then not any other way, <hi>Act.</hi> 8. and the believing <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> were called by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; and ſo were all the Churches called to be Saints, how I pray you, if not by the Goſpels preaching? Nay, how ſhould we poor ſinners of the Gentiles have known of a door of hope open to us, but by the preaching of the Goſpel? nay ſhould we have known of a Chriſt that died at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> but by the Scripture? or, how ſhould we know ſin to be ſin, and righteouſneſs to be righteouſneſs, but by the Scripture?</p>
            <p>Again, ſee what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2 laſt verſ. <hi>All Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is given by inſpiration of God, and is profitable for do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs:</hi> minde, not that man is perfect; but, <hi>that he may be perfect, and thereby throughly furniſhed unto all good works.</hi> By all which it is plain, that the Scripture is of greater uſe then theſe men will have it. And Chriſt ſaith, <hi>The words that I have ſpoken the ſame ſhall judge you at the laſt day:</hi> and this word ſhall not return void, but ſhall be to all that entertain it a ſavour of life unto life, but to them that put it from them, and ſay it is uſeleſs, it will be a ſavour of death unto death.</p>
            <p>But to you who are through Grace members of the Church of Chriſt, who were once ſinners of the Gentiles, and without God in the world, but are now made nigh by the blood of his Son, as <hi>Paul</hi> witneſſes, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.11.</p>
            <p>It is good for us, that we have often in our meditations, the great uſe that the Scripture hath been to us, in helping us to know what ſin is, that ſo we may avoid it; and it alſo hath ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed what righteouſneſs is, that we may be in love with it. And
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:168186:16"/>I pray you let your former experiences of what good we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the word and Ordinances, not to be forgotten.</p>
            <p>And further, we finde and are made ſenſible through Grace, that the Scripture is and hath been a ſweet and perfect Rule for us to walk by, and we thereby have been led and guided into the way of Truth and Peace. And we know that all thoſe that are found faithful in obeying the commands of Chriſt, and continue therein, they ſhall receive a crown of glory that fadeth not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. And therefore let us alwayes look unto the Law and to the Teſtimony, and imbrace that ſweet counſel, for the tryal of all doctrines; for ſaith the Prophet, if any ſpeak not according to this, minde, when they come from hell and darkneſs, for ſaith he, they have no light in them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8.20. O! then all thoſe that go about to deſtroy this Rule, they are ſo in darkneſs, that as the Scripture ſaith, They know not at what they ſtumble, or whither they go, <hi>John</hi> 12.35.</p>
            <p>And though theſe men ſay, That <hi>they are the onely men that know God, and love God,</hi> yet if we ſee what <hi>John</hi> ſaith, it will be found otherwiſe, 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 2.3, 4, 5. <hi>Hereby,</hi> ſaith <hi>John</hi> to the Church, <hi>we do know, that we do know him,</hi> minde, <hi>if we keep his commandments; and he that ſaith, I know him, and keepeth not his commandments,</hi> what follows? <hi>he is a liar; and</hi> minde, ſuch a liar, that <hi>the truth is not in him. And he that ſaith, He abideth in him, ought himſelf ſo to walk, even as he walked.</hi> Now this was Chriſt's walk, to do the will of him that ſent him, then theſe men go not Chriſt's way, but their own, and walk by the imaginations of their own heart, rather then by the holy Commandments of Chriſt Jeſus. And alſo ſee who they are that love God, <hi>John</hi> 14.23, 24. and ſee who they are that are related to Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.50. He that doth the will of my Father, the ſame Man or Woman, is Chriſt's Brother and Siſter.</p>
            <p>And now having given you his Principles, as he then at the meeting in <hi>Harliſton</hi> did ſtand by to maintain, which before the cloſe you have them weighed, which thoſe Principles he ſaith he ownes in his Book, and ſee how they ſtand together.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:168186:16"/>
            <p>But now in the ſecond place, I come to anſwer to thoſe falſe ſlanders he charges me with in his Book.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he ſaith, That <hi>I came on purpoſe to that meeting to cavil, and oppoſe the Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, That the ground of my coming with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Friends, was to oppoſe all doctrines whatſoever, that was not warranted by the Word of God; and in ſo doing, I have one greater with me and for me, then all you that ſo maliciouſly ſpeak againſt me. But O <hi>Farnworth!</hi> take heed of boaſting ſo of perfection, until you ſhew better fruit; and when you come to ceaſe lying, I ſhall hope ſome better things of thee.</p>
            <p>Now the ſubſtance of thy diſcourſe before I queſtioned thee, was, That <hi>you did witneſs you were free from ſin, and in the poſſeſſion of the ſecond Covenant.</hi> Then did I bring in thoſe words of <hi>John,</hi> and told you, That <hi>if it were ſo with you, then you had attained higher,</hi> I ſaid, <hi>then that eminent Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi> John <hi>had.</hi> And therefore thou dealeſt wickedly, to ſay, <hi>I brought it in to plead a continuance in ſin:</hi> ſurely, that light which thou ſayeſt is in thee, is darkneſs, elſe thou wouldſt not have ſpoken thus falſly: but having treated on this before, I paſs it by. Again, I ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Where was your proof, that you was in this condition?</hi> Then he laid his hand on his heart, and ſaid, <hi>I witneſs this.</hi> Then I ſaid to the people, That <hi>to truſt his own bare teſtimony without Scripture, we ſhould leave the word of God and truſt the word of a man, and ſo bring our ſelves under that curſe,</hi> Jer. 17.5. <hi>Curſed be he that truſteth in man.</hi> And alſo ſaid, as <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaith in that 17 chap. <hi>The heart is deceitful. And therefore it was good for us to try our own and others by the Scripture.</hi> Read <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.26.</p>
            <p>Then thou, <hi>Farnworth</hi> ſaidſt, <hi>I told thee of a Church in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Yea, Chriſt had a Church in the world, though not of the world; but gathered out of the world: and for the ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of it, did not the holy Ghoſt ſay, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.2. <hi>Separate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:168186:17"/>me Barnabas and Saul, for the work whereunto I have called them.</hi> And I am ſure, that <hi>Paul</hi> makes this good by many Scriptures, that he was a Planter of a viſible Church. But thou ſayeſt in thy book, That <hi>the Officers and Overſeers of the Church of Chriſt were inviſible:</hi> and why? <hi>becauſe made by the holy Ghoſt which is inviſible.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here the Reader may plainly ſee thy folly; for as I have already proved a viſible Church, ſo I will prove viſible Officers; as, what was <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> but viſible men? elſe their e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies could not have perſecuted them. And read <hi>Acts</hi> 6.2. <hi>Then the twelve called the multitude of the diſciples unto them.</hi> By which it is plain, this Church were made up of a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible company. <hi>And the Apoſtle ſaid unto them, Look you out among you ſeven men of honeſt report, full of the holy Ghoſt. And the ſaying pleaſed the multitude, and they choſe Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen with others, who are ſaid to be full of the holy Ghost.</hi> So that it is a clear Truth, That viſible men were here found in this Church made viſible Officers. But <hi>Farnworth,</hi> take heed of ſcorning ſo clear a Truth.</p>
            <p>But one thing Reader, I pray you obſerve; if it be ſo as <hi>Farn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth</hi> ſaith, That the Officers of the Church of Chriſt be inviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, then by his own grant he is none, becauſe he is a viſible man. And here is his folly made manifeſt. And alſo he denying a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, you may as plainly ſee from whence he is ſent, and whoſe errand he goes on: not of Chriſt's errand, for then his work would he do; but it is plain he is of his Father the Devil, who was a lyar from the beginning, elſe he would never ſay, that Chriſt had not a viſible Church; and ſay, all Ordinances ceaſed when Chriſt aſcended; and, that the Scripture would never bring a man to the knowledge of God; and ſay, that all Ordinances contained in the Scripture are carnal.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Farnworth</hi> ſaith in his Book, That <hi>I ſaid the Letter and the Spirit was inſeparable.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I do not ſo wonder of his taking boldneſs to lye of me, that dare ſo impudently lye of Chriſt, and of his Word and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances as he hath done.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:168186:17"/>
            <p>But to anſwer to this, thou chargeſt me with this, I then ſaid unto thee, as I now ſay, That <hi>the Word and Spirtt were one or inſeparable, and this,</hi> I ſaid, <hi>I will prove by the word of God,</hi> 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.7. <hi>For there are three that bear record in heaven, the Father, the Word and the Holy Ghoſt; and theſe three are one.</hi> And further, when I ſaid this, then thou <hi>Farnwarth</hi> pulledſt out thy <hi>Bible,</hi> and not before, and laid it on the ground, and ſaidſt to the people, <hi>If that be Spirit and Life, it would riſe it ſelf.</hi> I told thee at that time, <hi>That what was contained in that book, which it declared of, and held out to us, was Spirit and Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here Reader, take not my words, but the words of Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 6.63. <hi>The words that I ſpeak unto you, they are ſpirit, and they are life;</hi> minde, that which Chriſt ſpake they are, and compare this with <hi>Job.</hi> 12.48. <hi>The words,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>that I have ſpoken,</hi> minde that, <hi>the ſame ſhall judge you at the laſt day:</hi> which word is eſtabliſhed in heaven, and written for our learning, and is a perfect rule for us to walk by: and ſee what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4. <hi>For whatever were written ofore time were written for our learning, that we through patience and comfort of the Scriptures might have hope.</hi> And minde what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the Church, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.32. at his departure, <hi>Now, brethren I commend you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to make you wiſe to ſalvation, and to build you up, &amp; to give you an inheritance among them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> commends <hi>Timothy,</hi> that from a childe he had known the holy Scripture; and, which is very obſervable, <hi>Paul</hi> preſſeth <hi>Timothy</hi> to continue in the things he had learned, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.13, 14, 15, 16. <hi>For,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>evil men and ſeducers ſhall wax worſe and worſe, deceiving and being deceived.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>Farnworth,</hi> it ſeems you have not learned to diſtinguiſh between Law and Goſpel; for I demand of thee, where any of the words of Chriſt or his Apoſtles are called Letter: ſee what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Our ſufficiency is of God, who hath made us able Miniſters of the New Teſtament; not of the letter that killeth, but of the ſpirit that giveth life.</hi> Now I am ſure if <hi>Paul</hi> &amp; the other Apoſtles were alive, you would call them Phariſees, and outward Jews, Miniſters of the Letter, and call Chriſt a Water-ma<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>r outſide-waſher, as you call me; for I am ſure, that they that carry on this work, they have their rules
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:168186:18"/>from Chriſt, and they are the onely wiſe men. And this I ſay, That for Baby-ſprinklers, and Tythe-takers, and Pariſh-men, we own no ſuch thing; and therefore let them runne in your number and ranke, as men refuſing and rejecting the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Ordinances of Chriſt as you do; onely this I believe, that many of them do what they do ignorantly: but I fear you do wilfully ſpeak againſt Truth.</p>
            <p>But O you Scorners, how long will you delight in your ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to call the Holy Scripture a dead Letter and carnal, as you do? But to all of you that are contentious, and do not obey the Truth, of what ranke ſoever you be, or by what name ſo ever called, ſee your portion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.8. <hi>Tribulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and anguiſh upon every ſoul of man that is contentious, and doth not obey the truth.</hi> And ſee what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Theſ</hi> 1.9. where he ſpeaks of ſome men that <hi>ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of his power:</hi> and minde who they are, verſ. 8. <hi>Them that know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> O then, what will you do, that ſpeak reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully againſt the Goſpel of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>But let me tell you, it is not all your ſayings, that can put off or defer the Lord's coming: and at that time ſhall the wicked be turned into hell, and all the people that forget God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9.17. with <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.6.</p>
            <p>Then thou <hi>Farnworth</hi> ſaidſt, <hi>I called the Bible a Hiſtory.</hi> Now let the Reader minde how this hangeth together: firſt, he ſaid, <hi>I ſet up the Letter, and made it one with the Spirit:</hi> and now ſaith, <hi>I call it a Hiſtory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, Reader, I will declare what I ſpake, when I proved what I ſaid all along by Scripture. He ſaid unto me, <hi>That is Letter, and that I had nothing to do with it, being ignorant of the myſtery.</hi> Then I ſaid, <hi>What will you call this? a Hiſtory?</hi> yet this I ſay, That if there be a myſtery in the Scripture, then there muſt be a Hiſtory, wherein it is kept, which doth declare of it: read, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5.31, 32. <hi>For this cauſe ſhall a man leave father and mother, and cleave to his wife, and they twain ſhall be one
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:168186:18"/>fleſh. This is a great myſtery, but I ſpeak concerning Chriſt and his Church.</hi> Compare this with <hi>Col.</hi> 1.21. <hi>And you who were ſometimes alienated and enemies in your minde, by wicked works, yet now he hath reconciled in the body of his fleſh through death, to preſent you holy, and unblamable, and unreproveable in his ſight,</hi> verſ. 22. <hi>Whereof I am made a Miniſter, according to the diſpenſation of God which is given to me for you, to fulfil the word of God,</hi> verſ. 23. <hi>Even the myſtery, which hath been hid from ages and from gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, but now is made manifeſt to his Saints; to whom God would make known, what is the riches of the glory of this myſtery among the Gentiles, which is Chriſt in you the hope of glory,</hi> verſ. 26, 27.</p>
            <p>Again, God manifeſt in fleſh is a myſtery, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.16. and the bringing in of the Gentiles into the Church, to be of Chriſt's body is called a myſtery: read <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.3, 4, 5, 6. and the word declares it.</p>
            <p>Dear Friends, minde the deſign of theſe men, that do not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſtroy the Ordinances of Chriſt, but Goſpel-Order alſo; as God is a God of order in all the Churches of the Saints, and we finde, that Chriſt came into all his Offices when he was on earth, in an orderly way, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.6. <hi>This is he that came by water and bood, even Jeſus Chriſt; not by water onely, but by water and blood: and it is the Spirit that beareth witneſs.</hi> Now this muſt needs be the coming of Chriſt into his Offices: for we know, that his coming into the world was as a man, and born of a Virgin; but his coming into his Offices by water and blood is witneſſed by the Spirit.</p>
            <p>And firſt, we will ſee how Chriſt came into his Prophetical Office; and that is plain, he came by Water: and the Spirit bears witneſs to it, ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 3.13. <hi>Then cometh Jeſus from Galilee to Jordan, to John, to be baptized of him.</hi> And there you may further minde, when <hi>John</hi> ſaid, <hi>I have need to be baptized of thee, and comeſt thou to me? Jeſus anſwered and ſaid, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer it to be ſo now, for it becometh us:</hi> minde, not he onely, but us; that is to ſay, all that will be followers of him. What is it that becomes us to do? <hi>To fulfil all righteouſneſs. Then
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:168186:19"/>he ſuffered him.</hi> And ſee how the Spirit witneſſes this orderly coming of Chriſt into his Prophetical Office, <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>And when he was baptized, he ſtraight way went up out of the water;</hi> minde that, no Font nor Baſon, for that could not contain him, as is well known: <hi>And to the heavens were opened unto him, and he ſaw the Spirit of God deſcending like a Dove, and lighting upon him.</hi> And further, ſee how the Father commend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this righteous act, in theſe words, <hi>Thou art my well-beloved Son, in whom I am well-pleaſed.</hi> Here the Lord ſo fully de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares him to be his Son in whom he is well-pleaſed, as is not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in the Scripture that ever he ſaid ſo before; though I grant that he were his beloved Son before, though not ſo declared unto us, till this obedience to this Ordinance. And ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.17. <hi>From that time Jeſus began preach, and to ſay, Repent, for the kingdom of God is nigh at hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>See Chriſts ſecond Office, that is his Prieſtly Office, and that he came into by his Blood, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.11. <hi>Christ is become an high Prieſt for ever of good things to come, not by the blood of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but by his own blood,</hi> verſ. 12. and this the Holy Ghoſt ſignified, <hi>v.</hi> 8. And read <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.14, 15. <hi>By one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are ſanctified: whereof the holy Ghoſt is witneſs to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And his third Office, namely, his Kingly Office, he came into at his Reſurrection, <hi>Matth.</hi> 28.18. <hi>All power is given to me in heaven and in earth.</hi> And by vertue of this Authority, he ſends out his Apoſtles to teach all Nations, baptizing them.</p>
            <p>But you <hi>Farnworth,</hi> and all thoſe with you, that go about to deſtroy order, that will not come into the Prophetical Office as Chriſt came into his, I dare be bold to ſay, you are no Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, but of Antichriſt; for you are ſelf-called, and not by the Church of Chriſt; and ſpeak viſions of your own heart, inſtead of the wholeſome words of Chriſt. Surely, you would call Chriſt and his Apoſtles Water-men and outſide-Waſhers, if they were now on earth. But you ſay, <hi>You have the bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of the Spirit, and therefore the other is nothing to you.</hi> Methinks you ſhould grant that Chriſt had more of the Spirit's baptiſm then ever you had; and yet we finde it kept him not from
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:168186:19"/>Water-baptiſm: but he layes a neceſſity of it, <hi>Suffer it to be ſo now, for it becometh us to fulfil all righteouſneſs.</hi> And we ſee <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaking to <hi>Cornelius</hi> and his houſhold, whom the Spirit was fallen upon, as on the Apoſtles at the beginning, <hi>Act.</hi> 11.15. yet this did not hinder them from Water-baptiſm, but rather fitted them for it: for ſaith <hi>Peter, Act.</hi> 10.47. <hi>Can any man for bid water,</hi> minde, <hi>that theſe ſhould not be baptized, which have received the Holy Ghoſt as well as we? And he commanded them to be baptized.</hi> Without queſtion, if <hi>Peter</hi> were now alive, you would ſay he were an Hypocrite, and one that reſted in the Letter; but indeed you ſhew your ſelves to be no Meſſengers of Chriſt; no, not qualified as the Prieſts un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Law; for they were ſuch as could have compaſſion of the ignorant, and of them that are out of the way; but where is your pity and tenderneſs towards any that are not ſo black-mouth'd as you, to rail againſt the Scripture and Ordinances, as you do?</p>
            <p>O poor Creatures! this I ſay of you, That ye be objects of pity, and not of puniſhment: for I believe, That Chriſt will never account ſuch worty to ſuffer for him, that ſo deal with him, and his Ordinances and Saints, as you do.</p>
            <p>And now to that other ſlander you caſt upon me in your book, ſaying, That <hi>I ſaid<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt had not judgement committed to him while he was upon earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But here you have ſpoken as falſly as you have in the other: but this I ſaid, That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt at his firſt coming came not ſpeedily to execute judgement upon all that did not receive him:</hi> for I ſay, It is clear to me by his own words, that his firſt coming was rather to ſave the world; &amp; for this, ſee Chriſts own words, <hi>John</hi> 12.46, 47. <hi>I am come a light into the wold, that whoſoever believeth on me ſhall not abide in darkneſs: and if any man hear my words, and believe not,</hi> minde what follows, <hi>I judge him not; for I came not to judge the world, but to ſave the world. He that rejecteth me, and receiveth not my words, hath one that judgeth him: the word that I have ſpoken, the ſame ſhall judge him in the laſt day.</hi> And Chriſt
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:168186:20"/>ſaith, <hi>I came to ſeek and to ſave that which was loſt,</hi> Matth. 18.11. And, <hi>To open the blinde eyes, and to bring priſoners from the priſon, and them that are in darkneſs out of the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon-houſe,</hi> Iſa. 42.7. And for this end, that is to ſay, his own glory, and for the good of poor Creatures, did he ſend his Son into the world: read <hi>John</hi> 3.16, 17. <hi>For God ſo loved the world, that he gave his onely begotten Son, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life: for God ſent not his Son into the world to condemn the world; but that the world through him might be ſaved.</hi> And having thus found out by the Scripture the end of God's ſending his Son into the world, and of Chriſt's coming; and it is plain, that neither Father nor Son did or doth take delight in the death of poor ſinners, but rather, that they repent and live. But to ſay, That Chriſt had not judgement committed to him while he was upon earth; this I did not ſay: for I ſay, That Chriſt had all power in Heaven and Earth committed to him. But as I have ſaid, ſo I ſay again, He came in an orderly way, and, as I may ſay, was willing to ſtay the good pleasure of his Father, and did not take the power of judgement into his hands ſo as to execute it, till it pleaſed the Father to give it to him, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>Now all power is given;</hi> minde, it came by gift, and that from the Father, <hi>Col.</hi> 1.19. <hi>It pleaſed the Father that in him,</hi> that is to ſay, his Son, <hi>ſhould all fulneſs dwell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this I ſay, That in reference to his God-head, he was equal with the Father: but as he took upon him our fleſh, he humbled himſelf, and became obedient to the will of his Father. And he himſelf ſaith, <hi>I came not to do my own will, but the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work,</hi> John 4.3, 4.</p>
            <p>And now having found out God's great love to us in ſending his Son, and for what end Jeſus Chriſt came into the world<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that they through him might be ſaved; and that he did not go about to judge or condemn to Hell immediately them that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed him; but prayed for his worſt enemies, <hi>Luk.</hi> 23. <hi>Father forgive them, for they know not what they do.</hi> And how full of pity was Chriſt for <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that did not pity themſelves;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:168186:20"/>ſee at large <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37. his bemoaning of them; and <hi>Luk.</hi> 19.41. you ſhall finde Chriſt weeping over them, or for them, and ſaying <hi>O that thou hadſt known in this thy day the things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to thy peace! but now they are hid from thy eyes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what will become of all thoſe that ſlight his firſt coming; wherein there is held out ſo much love to poor creatures? O, I ſay, His ſecond coming will be terrible to all thoſe that refuſe to own him for their Prophet and King, to teach them and to rule over them.</p>
            <p>But O <hi>Farnworth,</hi> what will all you do, that make it your work to draw away poor ſouls from the Word and Ordinances of Chriſt? I ſay, What will you do at that day when he cometh to render vengeance on all that obey not his Goſpel? let me tell you, It is not your ſaying, That you are paſt the eternal judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that will ſerve your turn: I am ſure, that when the books come to be open, &amp; every man to receive according to the works done in his own body, whether it be good, or whether it be evil, and receive accordingly; Your juſtifying your ſelves now, will not ſtand you then in any ſtead. And if you would caſt your eyes upon theſe words of Chriſt now in time, you might ſee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of pride, folly and ignorance in your ſelves, in truſting your own Teſtimony: read John 5.32, 33. <hi>If I bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my ſelf, my witneſs is not true; there is another that beareth witneſs of me; and I know, that the witneſs which witneſſeth of me is true.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Reader minde, firſt, The pride of theſe men, that will thus boaſt of perfection upon their own word, without any Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture-witneſs.</p>
            <p>Secondly, See their folly, in ſlighting all godly examples; for ſo it is, that ſuch precious words of Chriſt, ſo pure a pattern, is by this their Principle diſregarded.</p>
            <p>And ſo in the third place is their ignorance made manifeſt, and darkneſs diſcovered, that they will preſume above what is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and ſo follow their own imaginations, and refuſe ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious counſel as Jeſus Chriſt hath left for us in the Scripture of Truth. O then it is plain, that theſe men are of that number that hearken to lying vanities, and ſo forſake their own mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:168186:21"/>
            <p>But dear Friends, let us ſee what the Scripture ſaith; and if we be there enjoyned to follow godly patterns, we ſhall do well in hearkening to it, rather then to theſe men that ſpeak thus a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt examples: read 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. where Chriſt leaves us an example, that we ſhould follow his ſteps, who is a bleſſed pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern of patience unto us. Again, ſee <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Brethren be fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of me, and mark them which walk ſo as you have us for an enſample.</hi> And ſee how <hi>Paul</hi> commends the <hi>Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 1.7. ſaying, That <hi>they were enſamples to all that believed in Macedonia and Achaia.</hi> And in his 2 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 3. ſee how the Apoſtle carried themſelves, labouring night and day, that they might not be chargeable: and ſee the reaſon, that the Church might obſerve this their good example, and follow them therein.</p>
            <p>Again, poor Creature, conſider, how thou judgeſt all men by theſe terms, of dippers, ſprinklers and water-baptizers, to be all of them in one nature, perſecutors of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, ſee thy folly in ranking all thoſe that follow the holy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments of Chriſt, with theſe ſprinklers that have not any word of Chriſt for their rule and practice, which thou knoweſt we own not.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſee thy ignorance in judging all, without making a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difference: for here thou muſt needs judge very many that thou didſt never know or hear of, and ſo art guilty of this ſin, in ſpeaking evil of them that thou knoweſt not.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, thou giveſt all men to underſtand, that thou owneſt not the word of God for thy rule, in condemning all that follow the Ordinances as they were delivered by Chriſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually with thoſe that obſerve traditions of men in the worſhip of God, as Pope, Prelate, and other ſprinklers do.</p>
            <p>And again, thou ſayeſt <hi>Where did any of us water-baptizers caſt out devils, and drink any deadly thing, and it not hurt us? And where did we ſhake the room when we aſſembled? And where did we give the Holy Ghost?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All ſuch unlearned queſtions as theſe, I ſhall anſwer in a few
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:168186:21"/>words, thus: Theſe things at the firſt, namely Miracles, were for the confirmation of the Goſpel; and ſo we may ſee the Law was at the firſt confirmed by Miracles: read <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.18. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.18, to the 22. ſo we finde Baptiſm was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Miracles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.16, 17. with <hi>Luke</hi> 3.21, 22. and ſo was Prayer, Preaching, and Laying on of Hands, at the firſt, confirmed to us by Miracles: and that it was for this end, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Goſpel, read <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.3, 4. <hi>How ſhall we eſcape if we neglect ſo great ſalvation, which at the firſt began to be ſpoken by the Lord, and was confirmed to us by them that heard him? God alſo bearing them witneſs, both with ſigns and wonders, and with divers miracles, and gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, according to his own will.</hi> And this is ſuch ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to us, that it is the word of God, that we need not look for a new confirmation of it; but we have recourſe to all the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments and Ordinances of Chriſt as they are written; and read <hi>Mark</hi> 16.17, 18, 19, 20. and you will finde, thoſe ſigns were onely to confirm the word. But it lies upon you, <hi>Farn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worth,</hi> and all thoſe that go about to deſtroy the holy Scripture and Ordinances thereof: I ſay, it lies upon you to ſhew us ſuch a confirmation of that which you bring, and then we may come to give more credit to your words. But for many of theſe Queſtions, I do not look upon them worth anſwering.</p>
            <p>But one word to you of the Church of Chriſt: I pray you let us minde what <hi>Iſrael</hi> did in the dayes of <hi>Hezekiah:</hi> when li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty was proclaimed by the King, that the Paſſeover ſhould be kept at <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> we finde that the people did not look for a new confirmation, but they had a care to keep it in ſuch ſort as it was written. And we finde, that by reaſon of wicked Kings that was before, the practiſe of it was loſt, in ſuch ſort as it is written, from the dayes of <hi>Solomon</hi> to the reign of <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> there was many yeers: during the reign of about fourteen Kings, was, I ſay, this practiſe loſt, as it is witneſſed 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30.5. compared with <hi>verſ.</hi> 26. yet we finde notwithſtanding, what they had ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the dayes of Tyranny; yet I ſay when liberty was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, they had then a care to keep it in ſuch ſort as it was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, without looking for a new confirmation, it being before con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:168186:22"/>unto them. And ſee how this their practiſe pleaſed the Lord, <hi>verſ.</hi> 27. <hi>Their voice was heard, and their prayer came up to Heaven.</hi> O! may not we in theſe dayes, learn much from theſe words? have not we lived in the dayes paſt under Tyrants, and by their means the Ordinances of Chriſt as they were practiſed by him and his Apoſtles, I ſay, by reaſon of former Tyranny, it hath not been of a long time obſerved in ſuch ſort as Chriſt hath commanded; but now hath the Lord brought us to a day of liberty, and that by eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>O then in the firſt place, let us give the Lord praiſe, who hath dealt ſo bountifully with us, as to ſet us at liberty from ſo great Oppreſſors.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Let us learn to keep the Commandments and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt according to his appointment.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us be ſure that we fight againſt falſe worſhips with ſpiritual weapons, and no other wayes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Take heed of ſetting up your ſelves or your own practices in the worſhiping of God, to infringe the liberties of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and for thy help herein, minde that ſweet counſel of Chriſt <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.12. <hi>Therefore all things whatſoever ye would that men ſhould do to you, do ye even ſo to them: for this is the Law and the Prophets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, Labour to walk humbly before God, and thankfully to God continually, ſpeaking well of his Name: it is the onely way to enjoy greater mercies from him. We of this Nation have as great if not greater<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cauſe of returning praiſe to the Lord, then <hi>Iſrael</hi> had. O that we could in the fear of the Lord weigh our mercies with thoſe ſpoken of by <hi>David,</hi> Pſ. 107. And we may ſay, that what the Lord then did for <hi>Iſrael,</hi> he hath now done for <hi>England.</hi> I deſire the Reader to weigh thoſe words well, and we may plainly ſee that it is our duty to praiſe him for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and declare his wonderful works done in our dayes to the ſons of men. O that we were wiſe to obſerve the dealings of God, and his mercies beſtowed upon us in this generation!</p>
            <p>Sixthly, You that profeſs to know God and Chriſt, of what ranke or imployment ſoever ye be, labour to be of a peaceable ſpirit, as much as in you lies, live peaceably with all men; for let me tell you, if any be otherwayes minded in thirſting after blood,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:168186:22"/>ſuch, I ſay, will be very unfit to follow Chriſt at his coming, who is the prince of peace. And I pray you minde what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Tit.</hi> 3.1, 2. <hi>Put them in minde to be ſubject to principali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and powers, to obey Magiſtrates, to be ready to every good work, to ſpeak evil of no man, to be no brawlers, but gentle, ſhewing meekneſs to all men.</hi> And again, conſider what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. When Rulers are for the puniſhing of evil doers and for the praiſe of them that do well, then ought every one profeſſing Chriſt to be ſubject, not onely for wrath, but alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience ſake. O what cauſe of rejoycing have the Lords people to ſee how time after time there is a generation of men laying out themſelves to deprive the Lord's people of this liberty, that we at this day enjoy! Conſider how the Lord hath found out inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments all along to be as a wall between you and them. O praiſe the Lord for ſuch inſtruments.</p>
            <p>Now in the next place, I ſhall give an Anſwer briefly to that ſaying of <hi>Paul, Chriſt ſent me not to baptiſe but to preach,</hi> 1 Cor. 1.17.</p>
            <p>I anſwer briefly, firſt, It is clear that <hi>Paul</hi> was an Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, as is undeniable; if ſo, then he was as much con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in the commiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. 19. as any other: then minde thoſe words, and you will finde preaching and baptizing joyned together, <hi>And, Paul commanded to preach the whole counſel of God:</hi> and this was one part of God's counſel, that believers ſhould be baptized, as read <hi>Acts</hi> 10.47, 48.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If <hi>Paul</hi> was fit to be imployed in the greater, then I am ſure this leſſer is required. But he was imployed in the greater, that is to ſay, to preach the Goſpel; then Baptiſme, which is the leſſer, is required of him, I ſay, by vertue of the commiſſion, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.19.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Minde the reaſon why <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks theſe words, <hi>Chriſt ſent me not to baptiſe, but to preach;</hi> becauſe theſe <hi>Corinthians</hi> were ſo ready to ſet up men, as you may ſee 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 12.13. <hi>Paul</hi> tells them, Is Chriſt divided? was <hi>Paul</hi> crucified for you? or, were ye baptized in the Name of <hi>Paul?</hi> And
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:168186:23"/>this was the reaſon why <hi>Paul</hi> thanks God he baptized no more of them, <hi>Leſt any ſhould ſay, That I had baptized in my own name.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, If the words be honeſtly interpreted, they will hold out thus much, that preaching to the dark world that lieth in wickedneſs, is the great work; and ſo, ſuch men as <hi>Paul</hi> fit to be imployed in it: and to baptize, that might be carried on with any other Diſciple that did accompany <hi>Paul</hi> in this great work.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, If you minde the Greek Notes on the Margin of <hi>Can</hi>'s Bibles, it is thus read, <hi>verſe</hi> 14. <hi>I thank God that ye were baptized.</hi> And this is then plain, That <hi>Paul</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded that it ſhould be preached and practiſed, and this is all the reaſon why <hi>Paul</hi> thanks God that he did it not, leſt any ſhould ſay I did it in my own name.</p>
            <p>In the ſixth place, conſider that Text, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.24. <hi>I am not ſent, but to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi> And he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 10. <hi>Into any City of the Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans enter not, but go rather to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, I ſay, as the <hi>Jews</hi> were Chriſts own and he came of that ſtock, he came firſt and chiefly to turn them from their iniquity, as <hi>Paul</hi>'s work was firſtly and chiefly to preach the Goſpel, it being the great work; and that Chriſt was firſt ſent firſt to the <hi>Jews,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> was ſent firſt to preach, is plain, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.25, 26. that they might be bleſſed: <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto you firſt, God having raiſed up his Son, ſent him to bleſs you, in turning every one of you from his iniquity.</hi> But Chriſt is a light to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> though not there ſpoke of; for <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>God ſo loved the world,</hi> minde, <hi>that he ſent his Son to them;</hi> and ſo was <hi>Paul</hi> by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of Chriſt's Commiſſion ſent to baptize as well as preach: and you may as well ſay from that Text, That Chriſt was not ſent to any but to the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as to ſay, <hi>Paul</hi> was not ſent to baptize: for if you ſay, <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith ſo himſelf, who did well know his work, and how far his commiſſion extended, ſo may the ſame be ſaid, and more, of Chriſt. And now man ſtop thy mouth for ſhame, and ceaſe to cavil with Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:168186:23"/>
            <p>And whereas theſe men accuſe us for not uſing the term <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou</hi> to every man: and they ſay, That <hi>it is a ſin to uſe any other term to a ſingle perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, firſt, as to the term, I could my ſelf freely own it, as it is a proper ſpeech to a ſingle perſon: but for to ſay it is ſin, without any breach of a Law, I cannot believe it; for I will rather believe the words of <hi>Paul,</hi> then any of theſe men: read <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.15. <hi>Where there is no Law, there is no tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it may be ſaid, <hi>If we have any example, may not that binde us?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If in all ages we finde the Lord's people uſing this term, and they onely, then it is granted, that we erre in this thing. And for our clearer underſtanding herein, we will make ſearch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Scripture; and if there we finde the worſt of men as fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent in uſing of it, as the beſt of men, then the example is not binding. Before the flood, read <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.14. where <hi>Cain</hi> thoued God in theſe words, <hi>Thou haſt driven me out this day from the face of the earth.</hi> After the Law was given, there we finde in <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.13, 14. they whom the earth opened its mouth and ſwallowed up, they uſed this term to <hi>Moſes.</hi> And ſo read <hi>Saul</hi> and the Witch, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 28, 11, 12, 13 with <hi>Dan.</hi> 3. where the <hi>Caldeans</hi> the enemies of God's people, uſed this term as well as God's people: ſo read <hi>Matth.</hi> 4.6. the devil Thoued Chriſt; ſo perſecutors uſed this term, <hi>Acts</hi> 26.24, 25. where <hi>Festus</hi> ſaid, <hi>Paul, thou art beſide thy ſelf, much learning doth make thee mad:</hi> ſo read <hi>Mat.</hi> 8.29, where the devil ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>Art thou come to torment us before the time?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By all which I gather, That this term was generally uſed by all ſorts of men without offence, as the term You and Ye to a ſingle perſon, without offence is nationally practiſed amongſt us; but though theſe men cenſure us &amp; all men that go not their way, yet let us take <hi>Paul</hi>'s advice, I <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.32. <hi>Give none offence neither to the Jews, nor to the Gentiles, nor to the Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But if we conſider the way of theſe men, we may ſay as <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:168186:24"/>witneſſeth, <hi>chap.</hi> 23.24. <hi>They ſtrain at a gnat, and ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a camel.</hi> And if it ſhould be granted that this ſhould be, yet it will be much like the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>ver.</hi> 23. of this Chap. in their obſerving thoſe ſmall things, as the paying of Mint, and Rue, and Annis; but they omitted the great things, as Judgement, Mercy and Faith. And we will make ſearch into thy wayes, and you will be found a Phariſee in all theſe; for as they ſpake againſt the doctrine of Chriſt, and what was then practiſed by him and his Saints, ſo do you now judge us for fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the holy Commandments of Chriſt; and as they Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſees then judged all that went not their way, ſo do you, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling all men dead and carnal, and in the Serpents nature, under what form ſoever that differs from you.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to Mercy, you will be found not like thoſe Prieſts ſpoken of <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.1, 2. for they were ſuch as could have compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on the ignorant, and on them that are out of the way: but where is this compaſſion amongſt you towards them that go not your way? for you make it your work to turn men from the Truth, as it is recorded, and ſo are Phariſee-like, and without Mercy towards them that differ from you, as theſe were.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As to Faith, The Phariſees they were enemies to the Goſpels preaching by which Faith comes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 15. and they looked for juſtification by the Law, as you do now by fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the imaginations of an evil heart; &amp; as they ſpake againſt the Ordinances of Chriſt then, ſo do you now. And why? I ſay, There is an evil heart in you, becauſe I ſay many of you are now through unbelief departed from the pure way of the Lord, which evil heart the Church is adviſed to take heed of, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3.12.</p>
            <p>Or more briefly thus: The Phariſees they boaſted more of themſelves then any other people, as you may ſee in <hi>Luke</hi> 18.10, 11, 12. and all along in Chriſt's progreſs they were his great Enemies; and by their reſting in the Law, and ſpeaking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Goſpel, it is clear, they were corrupted in their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>And ſo are theſe men boaſting of perfection more then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people, as this Book declares, and in their whole progreſs they make it their whole work to overthrow the rule of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:168186:24"/>and all the Ordinances thereof, as they are recorded, and as Chriſt hath commanded us to obſerve to the end of the World, and ſo ſet up themſelves and their own fancyes, as the Phariſees did.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to Mercy, this was far from the Phariſees: read <hi>John</hi> 9.22. <hi>This they agreed of, that if any man did confeſs Chriſt, he ſhould be put of the out Synagogue;</hi> implying, that ſuch men were not fit to be communicated with; by which it is evident, that all mercy and pity to ſuch as forſaked them to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, was turned into hatred. And is not your mercy and pity turned into hatred towards all men that go not your way, but declare againſt it as they commanded, your mercy is turned into bitterneſs as appears by your words calling men devils, and Saints deceivers, and the Church of Chriſt Antichriſt, and the Goſpel Letter, and the Ordinances carnal; and ſo by your words we may eaſily ſee what your hearts be full of; inſtead of mercy, malice; inſtead of pity, perſecution; I mean, with the tongue, which is a weapon that ſtrikes deep; and ſuch hands I ſhall ſuſpect, if they had power, becauſe I cannot but ſee the heart filled with malice, by the filth that proceeds from their mouth: for ſee what <hi>Matthew</hi> witneſſes, <hi>chap.</hi> 12.33, to the 38. <hi>Out of the abundance of the heart, the mouth ſpeaketh. A good man out of the good treaſure of his heart bringeth forth good things; but an evil man out of the evil treaſure bringeth forth evil things.</hi> And if this be not evil, to ſay the Scripture is of no uſe to bring men to Chriſt; and, that Chriſt hath not a viſible Church in the World; and, that all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances ceaſed when Chriſt aſcended: I ſay, it is evident, this poor man is ſuch an Enemy to himſelf in ſo ſpeaking againſt the Truth, that mercy and good fruit is I fear far from him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, As to Faith, the Phariſees muſt needs be far from it, becauſe they were ſuch enemies to the Goſpels preaching, by which Faith comes: and that they were ſo, read <hi>Matth.</hi> 12.24. <hi>Mark</hi> 8.31. <hi>Acts</hi> 4.18. and by their putting the Goſpel far from them, they were in ſuch a ſad condition, that <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>They were broken off:</hi> and how? <hi>through unbelief:</hi> minde, and read <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.20. And thus by putting away the Goſpels preaching, they were without faith; and ſo all they did in the worſhip of God was nothing worth.</p>
            <pb n="40" facs="tcp:168186:25"/>
            <p>So you in denying that the Goſpel ſhould be preached or heard to this end that men may believe in Chriſt; I mean, the word of the holy Scripture, you your ſelves muſt needs be Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſee-like, far from Faith; and ſo like them alſo in this, in hindring others as much as poſſibly you can. Now as Faith in Chriſt is manifeſt in obedience to Chriſt, ſo ought all men to take the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for their rule in Faith and Obedience, and to obſerve what Chriſt hath in his word of Truth commanded. Then thou, <hi>Farnworth,</hi> and all the reſt that ſpeak againſt the words of Chriſt as they are recorded: are Phariſee-like without faith alſo. And to that Scripture, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.22, 23, 24. where the Author tells the Church of the <hi>Hebrews, They are come to mount Sion, and to the City of the living God, and to the heavenly Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp;c. I ſay, the Church of Chriſt are ſo come to mount <hi>Sion,</hi> as the Church of the <hi>Jews</hi> was come to Mount <hi>Sinai.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now let us minde what the Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 19.2. <hi>And the Lord called to him out of the mountain, ſaying, Thus ſhalt thou ſay to the children of Iſrael, Ye have ſeen what I did unto the Aegyptians, and how I bore you on eagles wings, and brought you unto my ſelf: now therefore if you will obey my voice indeed, and keep my covenant,</hi> then ſee what the Lord promiſed unto them, <hi>then ye ſhall be a peculiar treaſure unto me above all people; for all the earth is mine: and ye ſhall be unto me a kingdom of Prieſts &amp; an holy Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Theſe are the words which thou ſhalt ſpeak unto the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael.</hi> And compare this with <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. at large: but minde <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>Ye ſhall not add to word which I command you, neither ſhall you diminiſh ought from it; but keep the commandments of the Lord your God as I command you.</hi> And minde two great encouragements.</p>
            <p>The firſt is from <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. What people is there that have God ſo nigh unto them, as he is to us, if we walk in obedience to him?</p>
            <p>Secondly, he tells them, That all this Law is righteous which he ſet before them, that ſo they, might be in love with it. And you may ſee in chap 5, and 6. how fully <hi>Moſes</hi> holds out the Law to them; and they that were found abiding in it, and walk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by the rules thereof, all thoſe priviledges and promiſes afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:168186:25"/>they had an intereſt in: but thoſe that turned aſide from the holy Commandments, as the Lord had commanded by his ſervant <hi>Moſes,</hi> they, I ſay, were deprived of all thoſe privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and promiſes there ſpoken of; for with many of them God was not well pleaſed, for they were overthrown in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs. and read <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106. and 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.5, to the 13.</p>
            <p>So, I ſay, to the beſt of my underſtanding is the Church of Chriſt come to Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and it is clear, that Chriſt is King there by the Father's appointment, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 9. <hi>Rev.</hi> 15.3. And when Chriſt came into his Kingly Office, he gave out Ordinances for his Church to continue in; and to ſuch as are found doing his Commandments, and continue therein, they, I ſay, and only they, are within the pale of all thoſe priviledges &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes that the Scripture bears witneſs to, and declares of. Now ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 3.23. <hi>That ſoul that will not bear Jeſus Chriſt, that ſoul ſhall be cut off. And this is the winde of the Father, That his Son we ſhould hear in all things.</hi> And ſee what Chriſt layes upon his Church, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20. by way of duty, <hi>That they are to obſerve all things whatſoever I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded you.</hi> And they that come up to him in obedience, they, I ſay, have an intereſt in all thoſe priviledges; and my Reaſons are theſe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 1. Grounded on <hi>verſ.</hi> 25. having before held out the Promiſes; <hi>Now</hi> (ſaith be) <hi>ſee that ye refuſe not him that ſpeaketh:</hi> and then ſee how the holy Ghoſt in mindes the Church what ſad judgements befell them that refuſed him that ſpake <hi>on earth,</hi> which words relate to the Law given by <hi>Moſes: much more ſhall we not eſcape, if we turn away from him that ſpeaketh from heaven:</hi> for <hi>John</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Law came by Moſes, but Grace and Truth came by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> John 1.17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reaſ.</hi> 2. Grounded on <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. <hi>We receiving a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom which cannot be moved, let us have Grace, that we may ſerve God acceptably, with reverence and godly fear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But now the Queſtion between <hi>Farnworth</hi> and my ſelf, was <hi>Whether he was in the poſſeſſion of theſe priviledges he ſa<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he was?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:168186:26"/>
            <p>But Reader conſider, I pray you weigh the words a little with what he hath before affirmed, and you will finde he lyes, and ſpeaks not the Truth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, it is clear, That theſe promiſes are to a viſible Church, as the Law was given to a viſible Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> then he denying a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, he cannot have any right to theſe promiſes as he is a viſible man.</p>
            <p>Secondly, If theſe <hi>Hebrews</hi> had been in the poſſeſſion of theſe things, that is to ſay, the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> then for the holy Ghoſt to have warned them to take heed of refuſing him that ſpake from heaven, had been in vain.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Then they needed not that exhortation, <hi>To hold faſt Grace,</hi> as the Margin reads it; <hi>verſ.</hi> 28. <hi>That we may ſerve God acceptably;</hi> for that were fully done already if in the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The Scripture ſaith, All lyars are without; then they are not poſſeſſed of this enjoyment: and that <hi>Farnworth</hi> is a lyar, is plain, elſe he would never ſay, That all Ordinances ceaſed when Chriſt aſcended; and, That Chriſt hath not a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church: and ſee what lyars ſhall be poſſeſſed of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.8. <hi>They ſhall have their part in the lake that burneth with fire and brimſtone for ever, which is the ſecond death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, If they, and onely they are bleſſed, that do his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, and they ſhall have right to the Tree Life, then there is nothing but Curſes, Woes and Miſery to all them that make it their work to keep poor ſouls out of theſe promiſes, by perſwading them to a ſlight eſteem of the Ordinances of Chriſt. And here is the pride of theſe men diſcovered, that will boaſt of priviledges before they have any right to them.</p>
            <p>In the next place, I ſhall ſpeak a word of perfection. And this I ſay, That I own a perfection in Chriſt to be attainable in this life, thus: that is to ſay, by believing in Chriſt, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to Chriſt: add this <hi>James</hi> tells us, That <hi>Abraham's faith wrought with his works: &amp; by works was faith made perfect. And Abraham believed God, and it was imputed to him for righteouſneſs: and he was called the friend of God,</hi> Jam. 2.22, 23. Now I ſay, this faith that worketh by love, perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:168186:26"/>that ſoul wherein it is, to yield obedience to Chriſt; and God the Father is fully ſatisfied with his Son in the behalf of ſuch a one. Now I ſay, that ſuch a one may ſlip through infirmity or neglect of duty to God: but ſee what <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaith to ſuch, 1 <hi>Ep.</hi> 1.9. <hi>If we confeſs our ſins, he is faithful and juſt to for give us our ſins, &amp; to cleanſe us from all unrighteouſneſs. And this is by Ieſus Chriſt, whom God hath ſet forth to be a propitiati-through faith in his blood, to declare his righteouſneſs for the remiſſion of ſins that are paſt, through the forbearance of God. To declare, I ſay, at this time his righteouſneſs, that he might be juſt, and the juſtifier of him which believeth in Ieſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And truly Reader, for my part, I know no way to attain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, but by believing in Chriſt, and yeilding obedience to Chriſt; and this I own: the Goſpels preaching doth fully hold out the great love of the Father in giving his Son to die for us; which Goſpel being preached, is the means of faith, and is a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect rule for all to walk by. But for a perfection in glory to be attained on this ſide the Grave, this I utterly diſown. As alſo what <hi>Farnworth</hi> ſaid to me at <hi>Harliſton,</hi> That <hi>the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and eternal judgement was then paſt in him;</hi> I own not but diſown; for I believe the <hi>reſurrection of the dead, both of the juſt and of the unjuſt,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Act.</hi> 24.15.</p>
            <p>And now Reader, you having a view of theſe men, that their principles are very unſound: and why? I ſay, theſe men, becauſe what <hi>Farnworth</hi> then affirmed, others of his company ſtood by to maintain. And in a few words, I ſhall give you briefly what one <hi>Daniel Bott</hi> a brother in the Goſpel, reſident at a Town neer <hi>Tamworth</hi> in <hi>Warwickſhire,</hi> who was once deluded by them, but now through mercy is brought back, to the joy of his heart, and rejoycing of the Lord's people; and this I received from his own moth, That the ſaid <hi>Farnworth</hi> and others did preſs him to lay aſide the form of Scripture, and he would (they ſaid) have viſions and revelations immediately. Now conſider, Reader, whither would they plunge a poor ſoul, if they can once bring him to ſlight that form of ſound words, and that form of doctrine which was delivered unto us?</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:168186:27"/>
            <p>And further, he ſaith to me, That <hi>he heard one</hi> George Fox <hi>ſay theſe words: I am that eternal Spirit that gave forth the Scripture:</hi> and he told me, <hi>He did believe, that</hi> Fox <hi>did think when he ſpake this, that there was none preſent but theſe of his own judgement.</hi> And I aſſure the Reader this, that I cannot gather that the ſaid <hi>Daniel</hi> doth ſpeak any thing out of malice; for I judge the man, to the beſt of my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, one truely fearing God, and one that can ſay much of their deluſions, and that they are falſe Prophers, by their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to turn him from conſenting to the wholeſome words of Chriſt, and that doctrine which is according to godlineſs.</p>
            <p>Now Reader, if thou doſt throughly conſider what is before laid down, that this <hi>Farnworth</hi> did ſtand by to maintain, you may plainly ſee what ſpirit this poor man is poſſeſſed with; and if it be the work of the Spirit of Truth, to lead his into all Truth, then this man is led by an evil Spirit; and this appears in its o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration; and by the evil fruit it brings forth, you may ſee what the Tree is. And this is evil to ſay, That all that is gotten from the Scripture, is but brain-knowledge, and a great deal of ſuch-like ſtuffe he is filled with. If any man make ſearch into them by queſtioning them, elſe let them alone in their road of ſpeaking, and they will preſent a fair gloſs before you. This I have experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of.</p>
            <p>And now Reader to his principles, that he ſaith in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of his book he owns, as worſhip in the Spirit he owns he ſaith.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To this, if the way of worſhip that Jeſus Chriſt hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded, and hath promiſed to be preſent with them that ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip him to the end of the world, be ſpiritual worſhip, which worſhip is plainly laid down in the Scripture; then all that refuſe to take the words of the Goſpel for their rule and direction in the worſhip of God, as thou <hi>Farnworth</hi> doſt ſay falſely, that ſay you own the worſhip in the Spirit, but by your denying the rules you are Phariſee-like, that ſay and do not.</p>
            <pb n="45" facs="tcp:168186:27"/>
            <p>Secondly, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Thou owneſt the Church of Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But here thou lyeſt, in thy ſaying Chriſt hath not a viſible Church, and ſo thou ſhutteſt thy ſelf out both of Church and Miniſtery of Chriſt by thy own grant, as being a viſible man.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>The teachings of Chriſt thou owneſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here thou ſpeakeſt a lye alſo, as is evident by thy calling the Ordinances carnal, which Chriſt taught his Diſciples, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. <hi>Mark</hi> 16.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Thou owneſt the baptiſm of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> But here thou lyeſt alſo; for believers to be baptized is by Chriſt's Commandment, and he gave himſelf and example to us herein; and this thou calleſt an image and idol.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Thou ſayeſt, <hi>Prayer in the Spirit thou owneſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Reader minde, for this man to pray for himſelf, &amp;c is perfect and freed from all acts of ſin, and paſt the eternal judgment, as he ſaith; then I ſay, by this we may ſee, that prayer is uſeleſs as to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and for his prayer for me, I do not deſire it, neither do I beleive it is his judgment to pray for others, by his wicked cenſuring all men that go not his way. But this I further ſay, That by his fruit he brings forth it is made evident, that he is a ſtranger to the Spirit of Truth; for this Spirit it leads into Truth, then it doth not lead out of the Truth; &amp; I demand of thee <hi>Farnworth</hi> where ever the Spirit of Truth did or doth contradict the written word. But to ask thee ſuch a Queſtion, who art, as it is evident, poſſeſt with a Spirit of error, I do not look for ſatisfaction from thee. And now Saints, you having briefly a diſcovery of this man's fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, let us labour to take <hi>Solomon</hi>'s counſel, <hi>Prov.</hi> 23.4. <hi>Ceaſe from thy own wiſdom:</hi> with Prov. 3.1. <hi>My ſon, forget not my law, but let thy heart keep my commandments.</hi> Verſ. 5.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:168186:28"/>
               <hi>Truſt in the Lord with all thy heart, and lean not to thy own underſtanding.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is high time for the Lords people to be continually upon their watch, now Satan is thus transforming himſelf like an Angel of light, that we be not overtaken with his devices; but this I hope, dear friends, you well know, that it becometh the Lord's people to ſpeak the things which become ſound doctrine, that ſo we may ſtop the mouthes of all our adverſaries: for now is that day come that <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.3 <hi>For the time will come when they will not endure wholeſome or ſound doctrine, but after their own luſts ſhall they heap to themſelves teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, having itching ears, and they ſhall turn away their ears from hearing the truth,</hi> then minde what ſuch come to, <hi>they ſhall be turned unto fables.</hi> And it is the Apoſtles counſel to the <hi>Hebrews, chap. 3.1 2. Take heed, brethren, leſt there be in any of you an evil heart of unbelief in departing from the living God:</hi> and for your direction herein, minde <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. <hi>But exhort one another dayly, while it is called to day, leſt any of you be hardened through the deceit fulneſs of ſin. For,</hi> verſ. 14. <hi>we are made partakers of Chriſt:</hi> How? <hi>if</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>we hold the beginning of our confidence ſtedfaſt unto the end.</hi> For as it is plainly laid down in this Chapter. That the unbelieving <hi>Iſraelites</hi> came ſhort of temporal <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an;</hi> ſo without queſtion will it be with all thoſe now, that turn back from the holy Commandments delivered unto them: <hi>For the juſt ſhall live:</hi> How? <hi>by faith; but if any man draws back:</hi> What follows? <hi>my ſoul ſhall have no pleaſure in him.</hi> Heb. 10.38. And he that once puts his hand to the Lord's plow and looks back, is not fit for the kingdom of God.</p>
            <p>And it is worth the obſerving, how <hi>Paul</hi> tells the <hi>Romans, chap.</hi> 1. 16. <hi>I am not aſhamed of the Goſpel of Chriſt, for it is the power of God unto ſalvation:</hi> to whom? <hi>to every one that believeth:</hi> minde that, <hi>for therein is the righteouſneſs of God revealed from faith; to faith, and</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul) as many as walk according to this rule, peace be unto them.</hi> And let us minde <hi>Paul</hi>'s counſel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.19. <hi>Let us therefore follow after the things that make for peace, and things where with one may edifie another.</hi> And as <hi>Paul</hi> adviſes the Church,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:168186:28"/>
               <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Whatſoever things are true, whatſoever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good report; if there be any vertue, &amp; it there be any praiſe, think on theſe things: thoſe things you have both learned and received and heard, and ſeen in me, do and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi> And as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid to the Church at his departure, <hi>Act.</hi> 20.32. ſo I ſay to you, <hi>Brethren, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to God, and to the word of his grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an inheritance among all them that are ſanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And to thou <hi>Farnworth,</hi> and the reſt that walk up and down and live idly without a calling, if you would obſerve the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture for your rule, you would ſee what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.10. <hi>For even when we were with you, this we commanded you, that if any would not work he ſhould not eat.</hi> O ſee thy folly in going about to deceive, which thou art not called to by God nor man according to the rule: and what would be the condition of all people in our Nation, if this were generally pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="48" facs="tcp:168186:29"/>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Certain CONSIDERATIONS and QUERIES.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dear Brother in the Lord,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>OUr neer relation that we have one to another in the bonds of the Goſpel, doth engage me to manifeſt my unfeigned love unto Chriſt and unto thee, in anſwering thy deſires in propounding ſome Queries, by which we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine and try the Spirits of theſe men, who ſay they are <hi>Jews</hi> and are not, that ſo they may be found liars, and their falſhood and folly may be made manifeſt, and all that yet fear the Lord may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of giving heed to their cunning-deviſed fables, leſt they be led away with the error of the wicked, and ſo fall from their own ſtedfaſtneſs: and to that end, my deſire is, that they will conſider their cunning craftineſs, wherewith they lie in wait to deceive, by handling the word of God deceitfully; ſometimes denying it to be of any authority at all, and ſometimes confeſſing it to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a declaration of the minde of God, but nothing compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to that light which is within them; yet other times they will make uſe of it for their own ends, that ſo they may (as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) <hi>by good words and fair ſpeeches, deceive the hearts of the ſimple.</hi> And therefore, that their ſnares may be broken, and poor ſouls delivered; I ſhall commit certain things in the firſt place to their conſiderations, who deſire to eſcape the error of the wicked, and to attain to the reſurrection of the juſt, by patient continuing in well doing, waiting for the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 1. The words of <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.13, 14, 15. that
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:168186:29"/>ſuch are falſe Apoſtles, deceitful workers transforming themſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt; (and no marvel) for the Devil him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf is transformed into an Angel of light, therefore it is no great thing, if his Miniſters be transformed into the Miniſters of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, whoſe end ſhall be according to their works. And that this is ſo,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 2. That all the falſe Prophets that came to deceive, did alwayes preach their lyes in the Name of the Lord; ſaying, <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord,</hi> when the Lord had not ſpoken: and thus they covered their deceits over with the Name of the Lord, and by that means led people away from the word of God, to walk after the imaginations of their own hearts, or light within them, and to deſpiſe the word of the Lord, even as theſe people do: ſee <hi>Jer.</hi> 23.16, 17.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 3. That this is alſo the work of deceivers now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Goſpel, to propheſie in the Name of Chriſt, yea, and to do wonderful works in his Name, and yet Chriſt bids them de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from him, for they were workers of iniquity, and he knew them not: ſee <hi>Matth.</hi> 7.22, 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 4. That all thoſe that teach in the Name of Chriſt, are commanded to preach the word of God and Chriſt, even the holy Scriptures, which are able to make us wiſe unto ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and if any man teach otherwiſe, and conſent not to whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome words, even the words of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the doctrine which is according to godlineſs, is he proud, or a fool, knowing nothing: ſee 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.3, 4.2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15, 16, 17. <hi>ch.</hi> 4. 1, 2 3.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 5. That when <hi>Paul</hi> left the Church in a dangerous condition, becauſe of deceivers that he knew would come after his departure, he did not commit them to the light within them, to be guided by that, but unto God, and to the word of his grace, ſaying, That was able to build them up, and to give them an inheritance amongſt them that are ſanctified: ſee <hi>Acts</hi> 20.32.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 6. That when Chriſt had to deal with thoſe that boaſted of the light within them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He anſwered, that <hi>if the light within them were darkneſs, how great was that darkneſs?</hi> from whence we may obſerve, that thoſe that pretend to walk by
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:168186:30"/>the light within them, were in the greateſt darkneſs, according to the words of Chriſt: ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 6.22, 23.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 7. That God hath ſent forth his Light and Truth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the World, to lead and guide men to his holy Hill, and to his Tabernacles; and that the Light which he hath ſent forth is his Word and Commandments: <hi>Thy word is a lampe to my feet, and a light to my path.</hi> Pſal. 119.105. <hi>And the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a lampe, and the law is light, and reproofs is the way of life,</hi> Prov. 6.23. by all which it is clear, that the light which is in a man, is not able to lead a man to happineſs; but the Word and Commandment of the Lord is able to ſave our ſouls if we receive it with meekneſs, <hi>James</hi> 1.21.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 8. That the Commandments of the Lord are pure en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightning the eyes; and the entrance of his words give light and underſtanding to the ſimple, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19.8. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.130. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let us, <hi>To the law and to the teſtimony; and if any man ſpeak not according to that, it is, becauſe there is no light in them,</hi> Iſa. 8.20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 9. That none of the true Prophets of the Lord that ever came after God had given forth his Law and Teſtimonyes by <hi>Moſes,</hi> did ever open their mouthes againſt it, to undervalue it, or turn peoples hearts away from it, to deſpiſe it, and to walk after the imaginations of their own hearts and light within them, as theſe people now, do.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 10. That it was the eminent work and evident mark of the falſe Prophets ſo to do; for which cauſe the curſe came upon them, and all the people that followed their pernicious wayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 11. That all thoſe Teachers now, that come after God hath given forth the Goſpel of Grace and Peace by Jeſus Chriſt, and do labour to turn peoples hearts from the pure Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments thereof, by deſpiſing and undervaluing it, by calling it ink and paper, and a dead letter, are falſe Apoſtles and deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful workers, although transformed into Miniſters of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, as the Devil himſelf is transformed into an Angel of light; which the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 1.8, 6. ſaith, Are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:168186:30"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Conſid.</hi> 12. That all thoſe Teachers that come from Chriſt, which contend earneſtly for the Faith once dlivered to the Saints, and do preach the wholeſome words of our Lord and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, and labour to perſwade people to hear his ſayings and do them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to walk in all his holy Commandments and Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; they are that true and faithful Servants of Jeſus Chriſt, the children of God, and the ſeed of the woman that the Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gon was wroth with, and made war againſt, becauſe they keep the Commandments of God, and have the teſtimony of Jeſus, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.17.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now I ſhall propound certain Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, with a deſire of an Anſwer.</head>
               <p n="1">1. WHether the Light that is in any man, if it be of God, doth not lead him to his Law and Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, and not from it as ſome affirm? <hi>See Iſa. 8.20.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Whether theſe men that deſpiſe and undervalue the holy Scriptures (preferring the Light that is within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, above and before the Scriptures,) whether, I ſay, we may not justly conclude, that their Light within them is darkneſs, and then, how great is that darkneſs? for if they ſpeak not according to this word, it is, becauſe there is no Light in them? <hi>ſee Matth. 6.23. compared with Iſa. 8.20.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. What true Light, which is of God, is there in any man, that the holy Scriptures doth not ſpeak, and declare according to <hi>Pſa. 119.130. The entrance of thy words giveth light, and giveth underſtanding to the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple? ſee alſo verſ. 105. with Pſal. 19.8. Prov. 6.23.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:168186:31"/>
               <p n="4">4. What doth that Light that is in any man teach him that is good, more then the holy Scriptures teacheth him? <hi>ſee</hi> Pſal. <hi>110.96. I have ſeen an end of all perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but thy commandment is exceeding broad.</hi> Now if an end of all perfection, then an end of that Light that theſe men pretend to have in them; but no end of Gods precepts, for they are exceeding broad.</p>
               <p n="5">5. What evil doth that Light, which is in any man, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove and forbid him to do, that the holy Scriptures doth not reprove and forbid? according to <hi>2 Tim. 3.16, 17. It is profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correcti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for inſtruction in righteouſneſs; that the man of God may be perfect,</hi> and <hi>throughly furniſhed unto good works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Whether was there not a greater Light in the Lord Chriſt, then ever was in any man elſe, or ever ſhall be? ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe Scriptures, <hi>John 1.9. chap. 8.12.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Whether did he not declare it, and make it manifeſt to the ſons of men, both by his words and actions, more then ever any man elſe could do? according to theſe Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, <hi>Joh. 12.49, 50. Whatſoever I ſpeak therefore, even as the Father ſaid unto me, ſo ſpeak I: and, as the Father gave me commandment, even ſo do I,</hi> chap. <hi>14.31.</hi> Again, <hi>All things that I have heard of my Father, I have made known unto you,</hi> chap. <hi>15.15.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Whether did not the Apostles of the Lord declare and testifie the ſame things to others, that they heard, and ſaw, and learned of him? according to theſe Scriptures, <hi>1 John 1.3.</hi> That which we have heard, which we have ſeen with our eyes, which we have looked upon, and our hands have handled of the word of life: <hi>That which we have ſeen and heard, declare we unto you:</hi> and
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:168186:31"/>
                  <hi>Acts 20.27. Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>He had not ſhunned to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare unto them all the counſell of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. Whether we came to know any of theſe things that Christ or his Diſciples did, or, whether we can know them, but by the holy Scriptures: or, how can we know, that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Christ or his Diſciples were ever in the world, but by the holy Scriptures? conſider and judge. If theſe things be ſo,</p>
               <p n="10">10. Then whether is there not a greater light ſhining to us in the face of Jeſus Christ, through the New Testa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he hath ſealed with his own blood, then we can poſsibly expect to come from the heart or brain of any man now living or to live untill Christ himſelf ſhall again ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear?</p>
               <p n="11">11. If a greater light now ſhineth through Chriſt by the New Teſtament then ever hath, or by men or Angels can ſhine to the ſons of men; then whether is it not folly and madneſs for any man now to refuſe this light of the glorious Goſpel of Jeſus Chriſt, to walk by the light and dictates of his own heart, which is deceitful and deſperately wicked, who can know it? <hi>Jer. 17.9.</hi> even as a man ſhould light a candle to walk by, when the ſun ſhineth in his full ſtrength.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Whether may we not now, according to <hi>Paul</hi>'s di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, <hi>Gal. 1.8, 9.</hi> account all men or Angels accurſed, that refuſe the light of the glorious Goſpel thus ſhining unto us, and chuſing rather to walk by another, that is to ſay, by the light within them?</p>
               <p>Laſtly, if the ſpirit of truth, when it cometh into a ſoul, ſhall lead him into all truth; then whether may we not ſafely conclude, that they have none of the ſpirit of God, which err from the truth of the Goſpel as it was once delivered to the Saints, and under value thoſe words of Chriſt, which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (who had the ſpirit without meaſure) ſaid, <hi>They are
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:168186:32"/>ſpirit and they are life:</hi> and if they were not ſo to any man, it was becauſe they believed not, <hi>John 6.63, 64.</hi> For how can we know, that the dead ſhall riſe and come to judgemens, but by the holy Scriptures of Truth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>This much by</hi> Henry Haggar, <hi>a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of the Lord JESUS CHRIST, and the Congregations of his Saints: with a deſire of an Anſwer by any who will, or can.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>ALthough there is much ſpoken in the former part of the Book in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the vain conceit &amp; impudedent
<pb facs="tcp:168186:32"/>practiſe of theſe fooliſh men, in uſing the term <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou</hi> to all ſingle perſons whatſoever, by which they break the Commandment of the Lord, which is, That <hi>we give no offence to Jew, nor Gentile, nor to the Church of God:</hi> Therefore I thought it fit to put down theſe following lines, to make their folly manifeſt. First, They affirm, that the word <hi>Thee</hi> and <hi>Thou</hi> is onely proper to a ſingle perſon, and none elſe; in which they belye the Scriptures, and deceive themſelves and others, as appeareth, thus: <hi>Deut. 25.17, 18. Remember what Amalek did unto</hi> Thee, <hi>how he met</hi> Thee <hi>by the way, and ſmote the hind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt of</hi> Thee, <hi>when</hi> Thou <hi>waſt faint and weary,</hi> &amp;c. Thus you ſee plainly the word <hi>Thee</hi> &amp; <hi>Thou,</hi> is as well pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to thouſands, as to a ſingle perſon: ſee alſo <hi>27.9, 10.</hi> Secondly, That the word
<pb facs="tcp:168186:33"/>or term <hi>You</hi> was uſed by Chriſt, and that to a ſingle perſon, is evident, <hi>Luk. 22.31.</hi> where Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Simon, Simon, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, Satan hath deſired to have</hi> You, <hi>that he might ſift</hi> You <hi>as wheat; but I have prayed for</hi> Thee, <hi>that</hi> Thy <hi>faith fail not.</hi> Here we ſee, that the Lord Chriſt uſed the word <hi>You,</hi> as well as the word <hi>Thee,</hi> to a ſingle perſon: by all which it is evident, that it is no ſin, nor yet an improper ſpeech, and therefore the people of God may and ought to uſe it upon occaſion: and they which do af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it to be a ſin, do blaſphemouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that Chriſt was a ſinner. And thus is their folly made manifeſt.</p>
            <signed>Henry Haggar.</signed>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
